<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The peoples plea for the exercise of prophesie. Against Mr. Iohn Yates his monopolie. / By Iohn Robinson.</title>
            <author>Robinson, John, 1575?-1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00623</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21115A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S94919</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">44920405</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 44920405</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173852</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00623)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173852)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2102:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The peoples plea for the exercise of prophesie. Against Mr. Iohn Yates his monopolie. / By Iohn Robinson.</title>
                  <author>Robinson, John, 1575?-1625.</author>
                  <author>Yates, John, d. ca. 1660.</author>
                  <author>Brewster, William, 1566 or 7-1644, printer, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 77, p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Brewster],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Leiden :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Title page within ornamental border; head and tail pieces, initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures:  A-E⁸ F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: overwritten, and with ms. notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Dr. Williams's Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Yates, John, d. ca. 1660.</term>
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Monopolies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173852:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173852:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PEOPLES PLEA <hi>FOR</hi> THE EXERCISE of Propheſie.</p>
            <p>Againſt M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn Yates</hi> his <hi>Monopolie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Iohn Robinſon.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. COR. 14.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Follow after charity, and deſire ſpirituall gifes, but rather that yee may propheſie.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the yeare 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:173852:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173852:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO MY CHRISTIAN <hi>FRIENDS IN NOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich, and theerabouts, Grace and ſalvation from the God and giver thereof.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat loving and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full remembrance, in which I alwaies haue you (my Chriſtian friends) provoketh me as continually to commend unto God your welfare, ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce greatly when I underſtand thereof, and ſpecially that your ſoules doe proſper. And as the proſperity of the ſoule is princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally furthered by the zealous preaching of the Goſpell, ſo hath it been matter of unfained reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing unto me, to heare how God hath of late ſtirred up amongſt
<pb facs="tcp:173852:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>you, divers inſtruments, whoſe zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous indevours hee hath uſed that way, and covering in mercy what is evill (of ignorance &amp; infirmity on their parts (I hope) in their ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, &amp; miniſtrations, doth bleſſe what is of himſelfe, to the good of his choſen. But as it falleth out in nature, that the pure waters draw of the tainture of the ſoyl through which they run; ſo with you it ſeemes, the pure truths of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell haue ſuffered by ſome, too great mixture with ſundry Popish errours about the Church and miniſtery, in and by which they are propounded: and this more eſpecially by M. <hi>Yates,</hi> a man of good gifts in himſelfe, and note amongſt you: pleading the cauſe of the Whoore of Babylon, the Church of Rome, as Chriſts wife, and of Antichriſts cleargie, as of Chriſts miniſtery. And as this clergies exaltation is not a little
<pb facs="tcp:173852:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>furthered by uſurpatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples liberty, which it ſwalloweth up, and thereby ſwelleth aboue proportion, ſo in all his pleading for the one, hee doth neceſſarily implead the other; and as in other things, ſo ſpecially in the exerciſe of Propheſie, or teaching in the church by an ordinary gift; in which every one that is able brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth his shot in due time and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for a ioynt feaſt of that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly repaſt, the word of God.</p>
            <p>The Arguments in his writing (ſent unto me by <hi>W. E.</hi> with his conſent, and that before the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate) I haue ſet down word for word, and anſwered: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with confirmed what I haue elſe where published in iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of this exerciſe againſt his exceptions and anſwers: which,
<note place="margin">In the <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </note> being ſcattered here and there in his large diſcourſe, and divers of them divers times repeated, I haue
<pb facs="tcp:173852:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>collected, contracted, and ſet in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly oppſition to their contrary Arguments: and that without any the leaſt wrong (to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) unto him or his cauſe; as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving left out nothing in his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which might ſeeme to bring advantage to his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Now if any shall aske me, why I haue not rather anſwered M. <hi>Hall</hi> his large and learned volume a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, and the generall cauſe which I profeſſe, my reaſons are, Firſt, becauſe it is a large volume ſo full farced by him, as it ſeemes, that he might prevent further anſwer. Secondly, his treatiſe is as much (and more immediately) againſt the Reformiſts, and their cauſe in the maine, as againſt us and ours. Thirdly, the truth requireth not that perſons, but things be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: and thing in it know I none not anſwerd in my <hi>Defence</hi> againſt M. <hi>Bernard.</hi> Laſtly, I doe put as
<pb facs="tcp:173852:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>great difference between him and M. <hi>Yates,</hi> as between a word-wiſe Oratour, both labouring more, and being better able to feed his Reader with the leaues of words, &amp; flowers of Rhetorick, then with the fruits of knowledge, as alſo ſtriving rather to oppreſſe the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his adverſary with falſe and proud reproches, then to convince his <hi>tenet</hi> by ſound Arguments: and between a man ſincerely zealous for the truth, and by his ſimple &amp; ſolid dealing by the Scriptures, as M. <hi>Yates</hi> doth, giving teſtimony of his unfained loue thereof. Which truth, my prayer to God is, that he, with my ſelfe, and all other ſo ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it, may find, and therein ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in all things.</p>
            <p>And for you (my Chriſtian friends) towards whom for your perſons, I am minded even as when I lived with you, be you ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished by me (which I alſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat
<pb facs="tcp:173852:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>at the hands of the Lord on your behalfe) that you carefully beware, leſt in any thing you fall from your ſtedfaſtneſſe; but, on the contrary, grow in grace, and in the knowledge and obedience of the Lord Ieſus in his whole revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led will. And let me the more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly exhort you hereunto, by how much the contrary evill is the more both dangerous &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. A man may fall forward, and in ſo doing, endanger his hands and face: but in falling backward, the danger is farre greater, as wee ſee in old <hi>Eli,</hi> of whom we read, that he <hi>fell backward, and his necke brake, and he died,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.18. And how common a thing it is for men amongſt you, and the whole land thorough, in their declining age, to decline in grace, wofull experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teacheth: there being few <hi>old Diſciples</hi> to be found, vvho in their age do hold the ſame temper
<pb facs="tcp:173852:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of zeale and goodneſſe which they had upon them in their yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger times: this being one maine reaſon thereof, That the meanes amongſt you are farre more for converſion then preſervation: and for birth, then nourishment: Whereas <hi>they</hi> (by the Lords graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſpenſation in the orderly ſtate of things) <hi>who are planted in the houſe of the Lord, in the Courts of our God, shall flourish, yea shall ſprout in old age, and are fat and greene, to shew that the Lord is iuſt, and with him is none unrighteouſneſſe. Pſalm.</hi> 92. Of this grace he vvho is the Authour and finisher of our faith, make both you and us partakers alwayes <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Robinſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:173852:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:173852:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ANSWERE TO THE ARGVMENTS laid downe by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iohn Yates,</hi> Preacher in Norwich, to proue ordinary Propheſie in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, <hi>out of office, vnlawfull: anſwered by</hi> Iohn Robinſon.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="1" type="argument">
                  <head>ARG. 1. <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. I. Yates.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ROM the Commiſſion of Chriſt</hi> Ioh. 20, v. 21, 22, 23 <hi>all Propheſie in publick is to remit, &amp; retain ſins: &amp; Chr. grants this power to none but ſuch as he ſends. v.</hi> 21. <hi>&amp; ordains thereunto v.</hi> 22. <hi>But men out of office are neither ſent nor or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned thereunto, therefore in publick ought not to meddle with the power of the keyes. I know the exception will bee this, that many out of office haue propheſied, the Scripture approving it. I anſwer, An ordinary rule is never infringed by an extraordinary example, but ever by an ordinary. To marry my ſiſter is inceſt; yet in</hi> Cain <hi>it was no inceſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the example was extraordinary. I may not ſteale, and yet it was lawfull for the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:173852:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Iewes to rob the Egiptians, becauſe that was Gods extraordinary permiſſion. Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry examples, as they make no rules; ſo they breake none: but ordinary examples muſt ever follow the rule: and if they doe not, they breake it. Chriſt therefore laying down a perpetuall rule of binding and looſing to all ſuch as are ſent and ordained either by himſelfe immediatly, or by ſuch as he ſhall poynt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, it muſt neceſſarily follow, that any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary example will breake this rule if it bee not framed accordingly: therefore I conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirme, that no ordinary propheſie ought to be out of office. As for extraordinary, that cannot oppoſe this rule, becauſe it is of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nature, and therefore is not to be limited within the compaſſe of an ordinary rule. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I anſwer, That all the propheſies out of office, were by the ſecret motion of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which was warrant for all ſuch as had no calling by office thereunto.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSW. I. Robinſon.</head>
                  <p>THat all <hi>propheſie in publicke</hi> (and in private alſo) <hi>is for the remitting and retaining of ſinnes,</hi> I acknowledge: but that <hi>Chriſt grants this power to none but to ſuch as he ſends and ordaines</hi> by the <hi>Commiſſion</hi> given <hi>Iohn.</hi> 20.21, &amp;c. I plainly deny, and require his proofe. He ſhould then grant it to none but to Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; for the commiſſion there given, is peculiar to ſuch, conveyed to them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:173852:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>from Chriſt, confirmed, by the miraculous inbreathing of the H. Ghoſt, &amp; by them to be exerciſed &amp; diſpenſed prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally towards unbeleevers; of all which nothing is common to ordinary officers. As Chriſt then giues power of binding &amp; looſing ſins to the Apoſtles there, ſo elſe where, to ordinary P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtors. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8. Elſe where to the whole Church gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one, <hi>Math.</hi> 15.17.18. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.6, 7, 8, 9, 10. And laſtly in other places to every faithfull brother confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.18.19. &amp;c. &amp; cap. 18.15. <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.3. And ſince the power of binding and looſing ſinnes is onely by way of manifeſtation, and declaration of the word of God, the law, and the Goſpell look unto whom the word of God is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, unto him the power of binding and looſing ſinnes is given, though to be uſed by divers ſtates of perſons, after a diverſe order: vvhich order doth in no ſort abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the being of the thing, but onely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues it from confuſion.</p>
                  <p>And where he takes it for granted th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> that the examples for propheſying out of office in the Scriptures, were extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as <hi>Cains marrying of his Siſter, and the Iewes</hi> (the Iſraelites he ſhould ſay) <hi>ſtealing from the Egiptians</hi> his compariſons are without compaſſe, &amp; his affirmation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trueth. Theſe their practiſes were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the light of nature, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:173852:8"/>law (then vvritten in the tables of mens hearts, and afterwards written in the tables of ſtone) ſaue as there was an extraordinary diſpenſation by the Lord of the Law, and God of nature: But what like is there in this, that a man (out of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice) having received a gift of God, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extraordinary, or ordinary) by which he is inabled to propheſy, that is to ſpeak to edification, exhortation, and comfort of of the Church, ſhould ſo uſe the ſame good gift of God, in his time, and order? VVhat Eclipſe is here, of the light of nature, or violation of naturall honeſty? If M. <hi>Yates</hi> had remembred the law vvhich forbad men <hi>to plough with an oxe and aſſe together</hi> Deu. 22.10. hee would not thus haue yoked together things of ſo unlike kinde.</p>
                  <p>And for the ſecret motion of the ſpirit by vvhich in his <hi>ſecond anſwer</hi> he affirmeth <hi>that all propheſies out of office were,</hi> he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth both that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is true, &amp; againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. For vvhat vvere theſe ſecret moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſpirit, but the Prophets zeal for Gods glory, and mans good? vvhich alſo vvere ſufficient on their part, for the uſe of the gift vvhether ordinary, or extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary; whether in men in office or out, it was not material. So that, for the uſe eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an extraordinary gift there vvas required (at leaſt at all times) no extraordinary mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſpirit, but onely that vvhich vvas, and is ordinary to them, and us. God
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:173852:8"/>therefore, for his own glory, &amp; the good of his people, giving the gift, vvhether extraordinarily or ordinarily unto a man; hee hath vvarrant ſufficient from his zeale to Gods glory, &amp; mans ſalvation, to uſe the ſame gift in his time, place, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Of vvhich hereafter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Yates. ARG. 2.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FROM the execution of a publick fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the Church. Prophecy ordinary is by preaching to bring the glad tydings of peace and good things to Gods people: and this the Apoſtle ſayes is not warrantable with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſending.</hi> Rom: 10.15. <hi>We muſt feed the flock becauſe we are ſet over it.</hi> Act. 20.20. <hi>to propheſy to Gods people is an honorable caling &amp; none ought to take it upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, but he that is called of God as was Aaron.</hi> Heb. 5.4. <hi>The place of Iudas is called a Charge. Act.</hi> 1.20. <hi>the Miniſters are the light of the world. Mat.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Starres in the right hand of Chriſt. Rev.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Iohn was a man ſent from God. Iohn.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Chriſt ſent his Apoſtles in the midſt of Wolues. Math.</hi> 10.16. <hi>I haue not ſent theſe Prophets, ſaith the Lord, and yet they ran. Ier.</hi> 23.2. <hi>as many as found not their Genealogy to be from Levi</hi> (from Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron he ſhould ſay) <hi>were put from the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. Neh:</hi> 7.64. <hi>All theſe places keep us to an ordinary rule, and for all ordinary prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying there can be no exception from it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an open breach thereof: as for all your pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of prophecying out of office, they are all of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:173852:9"/>them to bee underſtood of the extraordinary: which cannot bee tied to ordinary rules. For ſo we ſhould abridge God of his liberty: but we muſt beware of imitation, leſt we become licentious.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>HERE is a long harveſt for a ſmall croppe. All that can bee gathered hence either by reaping or gleaning is no more, then that no man may exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe a publick function, or office of mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery in the Church without a lawfull ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or calling from the Lord, by the means vvhich he hath ſanctified. VVhich as it concerneth M. <hi>Yates</hi> well to conſider of eſpecially, reckoning (as hee profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly doth) his Genealogy from the Pope of Rome: ſo doth it not impeach our Prophets at all, who haue a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full calling for the uſe of their gift, though not ſo ſolemne (neither need they) as they who are to exerciſe and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill a conſtant miniſtery, and charge. But for the word <hi>Sending,</hi> which he ſo much urgeth, it muſt be known, that, as all that teach lawfully whether in office or not, are ſent by Chriſt in reſpect of their perſonall gifts and graces: ſo ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry officers are not ſent by thoſe who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point them to miniſter as were the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Apoſtles ſent by Chriſt, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted them. Sending importeth a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:173852:9"/>of the ſent from the ſender to another, and ſo the Apoſtles were ſent by Chriſt to preach the goſpell to the Iewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles: but ſo are not Paſtors ſent by the Church (which calleth them) vnto others, but by her appoynted to miniſter to her ſelfe. They vvho vvere in their time Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, vvere firſt called in their perſons by Chriſt to bee diſciples, that as Apoſtles afterwards they might be ſent to miniſter: they vvho are Paſtors, are ſent by Chriſt, firſt as members, or in their perſons and perſonal gifts, that as Paſtors they may afterwards be called to miniſter. And that M. <hi>Yates</hi> may haue for the caling of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, wheron to inſiſt, thus we practiſe. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the exeerciſe of the publick Miniſtery ended, the rulers in the Chur. do publikly exhort, and require that ſuch of their own or other Church, as haue a gift to ſpeake to the edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the hearers, ſhould uſe the ſame: &amp; this according to that which is written, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where <hi>Paul and Barnabas comming into the Synagogue, the Rulers,</hi> after the work of the ordinary mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, was ended (conſidering them not as Apoſtles which they acknowledged not, but onely as men having gifts) <hi>ſent unto them, that if they had any word of exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the people, they ſhould ſay on:</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="3" type="argument">
                  <head>M. Yates. ARG. 3.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FRom the true cauſes of propheſy in the new teſtament, which are two, either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate revelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or impoſition of hands:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:173852:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>the firſt is Act.</hi> 2.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.44. <hi>the ſecond Act.</hi> 8.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.6. <hi>third cauſe of publick propheſy cannot be giuen: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ordinary propheſy in publick out of office being neyther by immediate revelation, nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands, is vnlawfull. You may ſay the contrary, but it will be without all warrant of the word.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>IN this Arg. are ſundry errors Logicall &amp; Theologicall And firſt, why doth he not make Chriſts breathing vpon the Apoſtles Ioh. 20. and the deſcending and ſitting of the cloven fiery tongues vpon them Act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. cauſes of propheſy as well as <hi>impoſition of hands?</hi> Secondly impoſition of hands is no cauſe at all of propheſy, to ſpeake properly, as M. yates ſhould doe, (affecting the name of a <hi>Logitian</hi>) It is no naturall cauſe, for to imagine that men tooke the holy Ghoſt in their hands, and reached it to others were ridiculous: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it a morall cauſe, as in which there are propounded no Arguments, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues of perſwaſion. It is ineeed no more then a ſigne denoteing the perſon; not a cauſe effecting the thing. Thirdly, if it were a cauſe, yet ſhould it not be made the member of a diviſion oppoſed to revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but a cauſe or means ſubordinate vnto it as vnto the end: ſince it ſerued to the conveing of the ſpirit, by which ſpirit all reuelation is, and by revelation all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:173852:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>extraordinary by immediate revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ordinary by mediate: both which the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were in the Church, as is the latter now euen in men out of office, by meanes of their ſtudy, and Gods bleſſing upon the ſame: elſe could there never be lawfull of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, Paſtor or Teacher choſen in the Church to the worlds end. The gift of propheſy comes not by the office, but being found in perſons before, makes them capable of the office by due means.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="4" type="argument">
                  <head>ARG. 4. <hi>M. Yates.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FRO Modiſtinction of ſpirituall gifts,</hi> 1. Cor. 12.4.5.6. <hi>verſe; gifts, admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations and operations. All theſe are to be referred to that general verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Gifts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this place muſt be but one kinde of ſpirituall gifts, and be diſtinguiſhed from the other two. The firſt then are meerly gifts: the ſecond, gifts &amp; offices together: the third, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the effect of a gift then the gift it ſelfe: and therefore the Holy Goſt knowing how to ſpeak aptly, gives more to the effect, then the cauſe: the worke then the worker: for in truth miraculous workes exceede all the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue that poſſibly can be imagined to be in a mere creature: and therfore it is only a paſsiue beliefe, or faith whereby man is rather a patient, then an agent in the worke. Theſe</hi> 3. <hi>generall heads are deuided again, or rather exemplified by many particulars: firſt, verſe</hi> 8.9.10. <hi>all lay downe a kinde of ſpirituall gifts
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:173852:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>firſt a word of wiſdome,</hi> 2. <hi>a word of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> 3. <hi>of miraclous faith,</hi> 4. <hi>of healeing.</hi> 5. <hi>operations of great works</hi> 6. <hi>propheſying,</hi> 7. <hi>diſcerning of ſpirits,</hi> 8. <hi>of tongues,</hi> 9. <hi>of interpretation. That ſome of theſe gifts are extraordinary no wiſe man will deny: yet that I may proue them all extraordinary, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider</hi> 3 <hi>things. Firſt, the cauſe: ſecondly, the effect: thirdly, the ſubiect. The cauſe without al doubt is the ſpirit; yet queſtion may be of the maner, &amp; meaſure For maner, whether the ſpirit alone or the ſpirit aſſiſting our induſtry, and pains. I ſay alone, becauſe all theſe effects depend equally vpon the ſame cauſe: and I haue no reaſon to ſay, that propheſy ſhould be more by my pains and induſtry, then ſtrange tongues, or any other gift: for then I ſhould magnifie the Holy Ghoſt in one gift more then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. That which is geuen by the ſole operation of the ſpirit is more then that which is come by through ordinary paynes. I Bleſſe God for his ordinary prouidence where my hand goes with the Lord in my ordinary affayres: But wherin I find the Lord do for me where I had no hand, there</hi> I <hi>ought to magnifie him much more: ſo in theſe gifts, if ſome were ordinary, ſome extraordinary, then the ſpirit ſhould not haue equal praiſe in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all. The orator prouing Caeſar to deſerue more prayſe for his clemency towards Marcellus then all his famous victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, vſeth the maner of the cauſe to ſhew it. In thy warrs, O Emperour, thou hadſt Captains, and ſouldiers, vertue and valour; weapons and munition, &amp;c. but ſparing Marcellus thou
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:173852:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>alone didſt it, to thee alone it belongs, and all the glory of it: ſo if propheſy in this place aboue all the reſt muſt come in for an ordinary gift, then may</hi> I <hi>ſay, O bleſſed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Propheſy is thy gift, yet do I acknowledge thy ordinary bleſſing upon my labours in this: but as for ſtrange tongues, and the reſt,</hi> I <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge they are thy meere gift, without all paine, and labour of mine, therefore the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter praiſe</hi> I <hi>giue thee. Were not this to diminiſh propheſy in regard of the reſt, which the H. Ghoſt prefers before them all? and therefore did ſhew as great power in that gift as in any other. The manner the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being all one in giving, the ſecond queſtion is whether they were given in the ſame meaſure.</hi> I <hi>anſwer, No,</hi> Rom. 12.6. <hi>and hereupon the Apoſtle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that one Prophet ſhould be ſubiect to another, &amp; willingly yeeld place to him, that had the greater meaſure.</hi> I <hi>leaue the cauſe &amp; come to the effects, which learned men cannot diſtinguiſh.</hi> I <hi>will ſhew you my iudgement, &amp; follow it as you pleaſe. To the two first gifts is given a word: by words we expreſſe our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, therfore the ſpirit doth not onely giue a gift, but an ability &amp; power to utter that gift for the greateſt good of the hearers. Brother, it is the part of a divine, to ſtudy for apt, and fit words; and indeed when God hath given us learning by exceeding great paines, yet wee find great imperfection for want of words. Now here I learne that the Spirit of God did extraordinarily ſupply this want, by giving un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men excellent utterance of heavenly things.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:173852:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>The firſt two gifts are wiſdom &amp; knowledge: wiſdom is a holy understanding of heavenly things with a prudent application of them to their ſeverall vſes. Knowledge, or ſcience is an inſight into divers heavenly truths, yet wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting that prudent application: theſe two gifts with a fruitful uttrance of them could be no ordinary gifts ſtudied out by their own pains, but ſuch as the H. Ghost did immediately inſpire into them. I ſhould be very glad to heare that your Congregations were full of theſe wiſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding men, then</hi> I <hi>doubt not but you would the ſooner recall your ſelues. The three next gifts, of faith, healing, and great workes are undoubtedly extraordinary, and were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to bee obtained, by any ſtudy of ours. For the foure last I doubt not but you will grant three of them extraordinary. Diſcerning of ſpirits was not by ordinary means but extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, as you may ſee in</hi> Ananias, <hi>and</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira, Simon Magus, <hi>and others, which were ſeene by an extraordinary Spirit. For ſtrange tongues,</hi> I <hi>hope you will not ſtand in granting it, if you conſider but the firſt ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of them</hi> Act. 2.2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>and for interpretation of theſe tongues that was as difficult as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: why ſhould you now ſtick at propheſy, which I will plainely ſhew was more difficult then both the reſt. For how ſhould either you or I come to be able to propheſy, except there were ſome skilfull in the originall tongues, as likewiſe the helpes of commentaries, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations? You ſee God appointed theſe as means to helpe us to propheſy and where they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:173852:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>are wanting, it is ſimply impoſſible for any man to become an ordinary Prophet: Indeed the H. Ghoſt can ſupply the want of both theſe: &amp; therefore will you, nill you, it muſt be granted that this propheſy was extraordinary. For take way the ordinary means of propheſy, and then the thing it ſelfe will ceaſe. Now you may plainly underſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that the Primitiue Chur. had not theſe means of propheſy, that you ſee we haue: they had not the originall tongues tranſlated, and therefore God gaue men extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary gifts in ſpeaking, and interpreting them: ſee then</hi> I <hi>entreat you how theſe two means being extraordinary inforce you to yeeld the other of the ſame nature. Were it poſſible for you to become a Prophet wanting the tranſlation of the new, and old Teſtament as likewiſe all interpretations, with which now through Gods bleſſing the whole world is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed? I know you will anſwer, and ſay no: then ſay, Propheſy in the Primitiue Church was extraordinary, becauſe the Gentiles had not ordinary tranſlations and interpretations of them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>IF I ſhould follow <hi>M.</hi> Yates in his courſe I ſhould rather write one Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon againſt an other then bring an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to an Argument. Briefly then, as I can, omitting other things, to that which concerns directly our preſent purpoſe. His affirmation that <hi>the gifts</hi> mentioned 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. are <hi>onely extraordinary,</hi> I doe deny:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:173852:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>and anſwer his reaſons as followeth. And firſt, that (contrary to his unreaſonable reaſon) we both <hi>may</hi> &amp; ought to <hi>magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the H. Ghoſt more in one gift then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> ſince the ſame H. Ghoſt worketh more excellently and for our good in one gift, then in another: And ſecondly (as a further truth and more contrary to his ſtrange aſſertion) that in ſome works of the Spirit, though not here expreſſed, in which the Lord uſeth our induſtry &amp; care, he is infinitly more to be magnified, then in any whatſoever the immediate and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous work of the ſame ſpirit, wherein he uſeth it not. For example, in ſaving faith and repentance: for the working of which by his ſpirit, God uſeth our careful hearing and meditation of his word, the Law and Goſpell. Thirdly, compare we even extraordinary gifts with extraordinary; we ſee, that God uſed the induſtry, and paines of the extraordinary Prophets for the reading and meditating in, and of the
<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.13</note> Law: and of the latter Prophets of the former Prophets
<note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>v.</hi> 2.</note> writings: As alſo of the Apoſtles in the
<note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> reading, knowledg and memory of them both: yea even of the very heathen authors, whoſe ſayings they ſometime quote in their propheſies or
<note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 17.28 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.33. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.12. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13.</note> ſermons: the like induſtry, or care not being required for the gift, or uſe of ſtrange tongues: and yet did the Holy Ghoſt much more excellently utter it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:173852:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſelfe in their Propheſies, and ſermons, then in ther tongues, as M. <hi>Yates</hi> oft, and truly affirmeth.</p>
                  <p>Vpon verſe. 8. he rightly deſcribeth <hi>wiſdome a holy vnderſtanding of heauenly things with a prudent application of them to their ſeverall vſes:</hi> and <hi>knowledge, an inſight into divers heavenly things, yet wanting that prudent application, with the fruitfull utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of them:</hi> but that <hi>theſe could be no or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gifts ſtudyed out by their own payns, but ſuch as the Holy Ghoſt did immediately inſpyre into them,</hi> he barely affirmeth; and I thinke, ſingularly; but am ſure, vntruly. I maruailed what he would ſay to theſe two gifts of <hi>wiſdom</hi> &amp; <hi>knowledge,</hi> to proue that they could not be ordinary: and did expect ſome ſpeciall reaſons for his ſo fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular interpretation: but behould a bare bone of affirmation brought by him without marrow, fleſh, ſkin, or colour of proofe. VVherein he is alſo the more blame-worthy, conſidering that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ignorant, how the moſt iudicious both at home, and abroad, doe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand theſe two gifts as meant of the two ſpeciall qualifications of the Paſtor, and Teacher; ordinary gifts of ordinary of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices: of which <hi>miniſterius</hi> amongſt the reſt ordayned by Chriſt the <hi>one Lord</hi> of his Church. the Apoſtle ſpeaketh verſe 5. as verſe. 4. of their <hi>gifts,</hi> by that <hi>one ſpirit.</hi> VVhich ordinary gifts all lawfull Paſtors, and Teachers (ordinary offices) then had,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:173852:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>and beſides them, many others not in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice? and by the grace of God, ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs: and that by the help of nature ſtudy and prayer, and the bleſſing of Gods ſpirit therevpon. VVhich bleſſing of God I will not deny to haue then been for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree extraordinary vpon mens weaker in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoures, for their furniſhing with theſe ordinary gifts: which makes nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our purpoſe. That <hi>the gift of faith is undoubtedly extraordinary is ſayd by him,</hi> but Doctors haue doubted of it. See for one, <hi>Beza</hi> in his great <hi>Annotations</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the words, both affirming, and proueing; that by <hi>faith</hi> is meant an <hi>aſſent vnto the doctrine propounded,</hi> which is an ordinary gift of the ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>VVhere he <hi>makes no doubt but wee will grant, that three of the foure laſt were extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary,</hi> he but threaps kindneſſe upon us, as we uſe to ſay. That <hi>Peters gift of diſcerning was extraordinary</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Ananias,</hi> Act <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> we confeſſe: but not ſo in the caſe of <hi>Simon Magus, Acts.</hi> 8. of whom he iudgeth by his words (as of the tree by the fruit) in which he did notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly bewray himſelfe to be in <hi>the gall of bitterneſſe,</hi> to the diſcerning of any ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Chriſtian. The <hi>gift of diſcerning</hi> both of doctrine and manners, is in a meaſure required of every Chriſtian. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.9.10. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.14. but is beſtowed by the giver thereof upon ſome more liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; ſometimes extraordinarily, as then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:173852:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſome in ſome caſes: ſometimes ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, as both then and now on all ſuch as had, and haue more Chriſtian diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then other men.</p>
                  <p>That <hi>interpretation of tongues</hi> was <hi>as dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult as ſtrange tongues immediatly inſpired,</hi> is not true. They who <hi>Acts</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. heard the Apoſtles ſpeake in their own tongue, and were able to ſpeake the Iewes language then in uſe, might interpret theſe ſtrange tongues unto the Iewes, without any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traord. gift: as M. <hi>Yates</hi> hearing a glorious Formaliſt ſpeak much Latin in his Sermon, can interpret that ſtrange tongue of his unto the people, without any extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gift of interpretation: and ſo might it well be in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> with ſome, though the tongue were given ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, it doth not <hi>ſhew plainly, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie was more difficult then ſtrange tongues,</hi> though all were true which he ſpeakes of the difficulty thereof. For by all reaſon and experience a man then might, and now may, become an ordinary Prophet for ability by ordinary helpes; but ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could, nor can hee ſpeake a ſtrange tongue, as there meant, but by extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary inſpiration. That ſimple neceſsity of <hi>Commentaries and Interpretations</hi> which he requireth for a mans becomming an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Prophet, I dare not acknowledge: of great uſe they are, but not of ſimple ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity: that prerogatiue royall of ſimply
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:173852:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>neceſſary, I would challenge as peculiar to the holy <hi>Scriptures;</hi> which are able to make <hi>the man of God perfect, fully furniſhed to every good worke.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.17. But where he addes, that <hi>the Primitiue Church had not the originall tongues tranſlated,</hi> it is ſomething for his, yea and for the Popes purpoſe alſo, if it bee true, and that the Church, eſpecially ſome good ſpace, after her conſtitution, might be without the Scriptures in a knowne tongue. But how unadviſed, and unskilfull is he in ſo ſaying? how detracting from Gods graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous providence towards his Church: and how partiall on the Clergies part, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Commonalty of Gods inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? For the thing then. The old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament was wholy tranſlated by the 70. Interpreters, at the inſtance of <hi>Ptolemy Philadelphus</hi> King of <hi>Egipt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioſeph Ant. l.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 24.25.</note> into <hi>Greeke</hi> the mother tongue of the <hi>Corinthians; Corinth</hi> being in <hi>Achaia,</hi> and <hi>Achaia</hi> in <hi>Greece:</hi> in which the ſame tongue they had alſo eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of the new Teſtament then writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, as the moſt was. VVhich language was alſo ſo univerſally known throughout the whole world, by reaſon partly of the Greeke Monarchy under <hi>Alexander,</hi> and partly of the Greeke learning at <hi>Athens,</hi> as that the Apoſtle could write his Epiſtle in Greek to the <hi>Romans,</hi> though in <hi>Europe,</hi> as underſtanding the tongue ſufficiently. Beſides, the <hi>Corinthians</hi> had had <hi>Pauls</hi> and other Apoſtolicall mens preachings, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:173852:15"/>conferences amongſt them a long time, which were uncomparably better then all the commentaries in the world. And for the Corinthians ability for this worke, it is but reaſon we reſpect this Apoſtles te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of them, which is, that they were <hi>enriched in all utterance, and in all knowledge,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4. In which two gifts as the abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity for ordinary propheſie doth properly conſiſt, ſo to appropriate them unto extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Prophets, conſidering the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the Apoſtles ſpeech, and drift, with other circumſtances elſe-where ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, were to fetter them in uniuſt bonds of reſtraint.</p>
                  <p>And having thus wiped off his colours of reaſon, that the Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. ſpeakes onely of extraordinary gifts, I will (by the grace of God) plainly ſhew the contrary, and that he ſpeakes of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary alſo.</p>
                  <p>And firſt, in teaching, v. 3. that <hi>no man can call Ieſus the Lord, but by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> he poynts out a gift and grace of the ſpirit, ordinary and common to all Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, v. 5 he ſpeakes of <hi>diverſities,</hi> that is, of all the divers and ſeverall miniſteries ordinary and extraordinary in the Church under Chriſt the <hi>Lord,</hi> and v. 4. of the ſeverall <hi>gifts</hi> for the ſame; and ſo neceſſarily of the ordinary gifts for the ordinary miniſteries, then and now.</p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:173852:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>Thirdly, from v. 8. where mention is made <hi>of the word of wiſedom, and the word of knowledge,</hi> ordinary gifts of ordinary perſons, both in and out of office, now, and then.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, v. 12. he compares the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> to a <hi>body,</hi> having <hi>Chriſt the head, and each of them members for their parts:</hi> of whom one had this gift, another that, given of God, for their mutuall good, but by them abuſed otherwiſe: whereupon I conclude, except there were in <hi>Corinth</hi> no ordinary gifts in Paſtors, Teachers, or others of God given, and by them abuſed, that he ſpeakes not of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary gifts onely.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, v. 28. after <hi>Apostles,</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> he mentioneth <hi>Teachers,</hi> which were ordinary officers, and therefore ſpeakes of ordinary gifts and teaching; as alſo <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> and <hi>Governours,</hi> who what were they but <hi>Deacons</hi> and <hi>Elders?</hi> or take the words as they are, <hi>Helpes</hi> and <hi>Governments:</hi> then which, what is now, or vvas then more ordinary, both in reſpect of miniſtery and gift? VVhereupon I conclude vvith good aſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ance, that the Apoſtle 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. treats of the gifts of the ſpirit, both extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and ordinary</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="5" type="argument">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Yates. ARG. 5.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FRom compariſon of propheſie &amp; ſtrange tongues which are laid together through all the</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>propheſie
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:173852:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>is preferred before all other ſpirituall gifts, which cannot be ordinary: for no ordinary and common gift is to be preferred before all extraordinary and ſpirituall gifts. But you will ſay, though it be not more excellent, yet it is more profitable: I anſwer, it is both more excellent and more profitable: for the Apoſtle intends both, extolling it for the end, which ſhewes how good and excellent it is, as likewiſe for the uſe, making known the profit and benefit of it. That which is the beſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of our deſire, muſt needs be the beſt: but of ſpirituall gifts, propheſie is the beſt obiect of our deſire,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.31. <hi>Deſire the beſt gifts, chap.</hi> 14.1. <hi>Covet ſpirituall gifts, but rather that yee may propheſie. Secondly, as it is the beſt to our ſelues, ſo is it the beſt to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as may appeare by the whole chapter. Thirdly, all other gifts are given for the good of propheſie, and not propheſie for them. As it is the beſt gift, ſo it is the moſt profitable, as being eſpecially for edification, exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and comfort. But it may be you will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect; Is not an ordinary gift of propheſie bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the extraordinary gift of tongues, or at leaſt more profitable? I anſwer, No: for the tongues, Actes</hi> 2.3.4. <hi>were more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Church then ever was the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gift of any man: but compare ordinary with ordinary, and extraordinary with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, and wee grant propheſie the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:173852:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>I. Rob.</hi> ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>TO this Argument he himſelf giues a ſufficient anſwer in our name; onely he ſets it down ſomething lamely; where if it came in the full ſtrength, it would eaſily with ſtand the force of his Argument. For where hee ſhould ſay for us, if he ſpake out, that ordinary propheſy is more excellent then tongues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe more profitable; hee makes us to ſtammer thus, <hi>though it be not more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, yet it is more profitable:</hi> it being moſt plaine, that the Apoſtle prefers propheſy before tongues, becauſe it tends more to edification of the Church according to vvhich reſpect alone vve are to meaſure the excellency of Church: ordinances, and ſo to frame the obiect of our deſire unto them. But vvhat ſpeake I of more excellent, and more to edification? ſince the ſtrange tongues as there uſed, vvithout an interpreter, were ſo far from being comparable to ordinary propheſie for any good end or uſe, as they were on the contrary moſt vaine and ridiculous, as appeares, v. 11.22.23. That then which hee brings for the commendation of tongues from <hi>Actes:</hi> 2. is nothing for tongues as uſed in <hi>Corinth.</hi> The former were, as of ſimple neceſsity in themſelues unto the Apoſtles, for the ſpreading of the Goſpell unto all nations, ſo then, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:173852:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>there profitably vſed: but in Corinth am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly and pr-ofanely abuſed, which M. <hi>Ya.</hi> ſhould haue obſerved, but hath not in his compariſon. Laſtly I add as a iuſt anſwer to whatſoeuer he hath obiected, That <hi>tongues</hi> confidered in themſelues, how rightly ſoeuer vſed, are not comparable for vſe and ſo for excellency, vnto ordinary propheſying or preaching conſidered in it ſelf: ſeing that by it as well as by extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary ſaving <hi>fayth</hi> is wrought Rom. 10. which none can ſay of ſtrange Tongues in themſelues, without a ſtrange Tongue both from truth and ſence: no nor of any other ſpirituall gift.</p>
                  <p>And as it doth not appear by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles preferring of propheſy before ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, that therefore the propheſy was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary; ſo it appeares unto mee by the Corinthians preferring of tongues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, that it was but ordinary: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore diſregarded by them in compariſon of the extraordinary, and miraculous gift of tongues: whereas, had it alſo been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, immediate and miraculous, moſt like it would haue carried with it the like with the other, or greater regard, in their eyes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="6" type="argument">
                  <head>M. Yates. ARGVM. 6.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FROM</hi> exemplification <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. <hi>if I come unto you &amp;c. I hope you will grant that the Apoſtle</hi> Paul <hi>had all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:173852:18"/>thoſe ſpirituall gifts, and therefore ſpeaking of ſuch propheſy as he had himſelfe, hee muſt needs ſpeak of extraordinary: likewiſe he had the knowledge of tongues and yet prefers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy before all his languages, though hee ſpake more then they all. Now the example in his own perſon muſt needs ſet forth the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall; and therefore if in the generall hee ſhould ſpeak of ordinary prophecying, &amp; in the particular of extraordinary, it would prove idle; for an example is of the ſame kind with the generall. Againe in bringing four par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars he puts revelation firſt, as the cauſe of all the reſt; which ſhewes plainely he ſpeaks of ſuch propheſy, as came by revelation for reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation brings a man to knowledge, and knowledge teacheth wholeſome doctrine, and propheſy ſerveth to utter it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>I. Rob.</hi> ANSVVER.</head>
                  <p>I doe plainely deny the ground upon which he builds the whole weight of his Argument which is, that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and the thing exemplified muſt be of the ſame kind. How oft doth Chriſt exemplify the ſufferings of his diſciples by his own ſufferings, and the ſending of his Apoſtles by his fathers ſending of him? were they therfore of the ſame kind; their ſufferings meritorious, and their ſending mediatorious, becauſe his was ſuch? But amongſt other evidences againſt him (wherewith all writings divine, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:173852:18"/>are ſtored) ſee one, fitly paring with this in hand. The Apoſtle prouoking the <hi>Galathians c.</hi> 1:6 unto iuſt deteſtation of ſuch as <hi>preached another Goſpell amongst them,</hi> takes an example from his own preaching, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>But though wee or an Angell, from heaven preach,</hi> another Goſpell <hi>unto you, then that which wee haue preached unto you, let him be accurſed.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, I haue preached unto you formerly iuſtification by faith without the works of the Law of <hi>Moſes:</hi> they now preach unto you iuſtification by the works of the law ioyned with Chriſt, &amp;c. He exemplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth their preaching by his: were they ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of one kind both Apoſtolical, becauſe <hi>Pauls</hi> was ſuch? It is ſufficient for an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple if it agree with the thing, which it is brought to exemplifie in that for which it is brought. And ſo the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt, to iudgement, is by the Apoſtle exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the comming of a thiefe in the night.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.2</note> Are therfore their commings of the ſame kind? or is it not ſufficient that being moſt contrary in their kinds, they do yet agree in the adiunct of ſuddeneſſe? So is it ſufficient, if <hi>Pauls</hi> extraordinary Propheſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the <hi>Corinthians</hi> ordinary, agree in the adiunct or effect of profitableneſſe, or <hi>edification,</hi> which thing alone the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in his exemplification hath reſpect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. His obſervation about <hi>Revelation</hi> ſeems true, and good in it ſelfe: but <hi>ſhewes</hi> not <hi>plainely</hi> that for which he brings it, no nor
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:173852:19"/>hath ſo much as a <hi>plaine ſhew</hi> for it. For what ſhew hath it of profe that he ſpeaks of extraordinary propheſie, becauſe it comes from revelation, except he takes it for granted, that there is in the Church no revelation of the ſpirit for teaching but extraordinary, or miraculous: which how can I grant, or hee affirme? Of this more Argum. 8.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="7" type="argument">
                  <head>M. Yates. ARG. 7.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FROM the fruition of ſpirituall gifts.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26. <hi>hath</hi> a Pſalm, <hi>that is ſome admirable praiſe of God, or doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, that is ſome worthy point of inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or a tongue, that is, can ſpeak miſteries with admiration, or revelation of ſome ſecrets either for doctrine or prediction; laſtly, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation whether of tongues, doctrines, or Scripture: all theſe muſt needs bee had either by the ordinary pains of the Church, or by the extraordinary gift of the ſpirit, you ſay by the one, and I by the other: and that I agree more with the Scripture then your ſelfe, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der but the diſtinction of the gifts, and their admirable matter. A Pſalm muſt needs conſiſt of meeter, which required art to compoſe it. Secondly, it could not for the matter of it, but ſound forth ſome worthy praiſe of God. Do you thinke the Corinthians did ſtudy the art of muſick, or likewiſe read ſome admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable divine bookes to finde out ſweet mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to make their ſongs of? Alas, brother, giue
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:173852:19"/>God the glory, it was no doubt ſome ſudden motion of the Spirit, that did inflame the hearts of beleevers with ſome worthy matter of praiſing God. Doctrine, that is layd down by our ordinary pains, is that which we uſually giue unto Doctors, which after long ſtudy, and reading the Scriptures is drawen to ſome profitable heads pithily proved, and contrary errours refuted by it. I think in Corinth there were none of theſe Doctours, and yet I doubt not but they were as excellent: for ſuch Doctors as delivered theſe doctrines had them after a more eaſie manner, even the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate worke of the ſpirit. I hope with out any further diſpute you will yeeld that the having of a a ſtrange tongue was extraordinary, as likewiſe the revelation and interpretation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>I. Rob.</hi> ANSVV.</head>
                  <p>NOT to meddle with his deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a <hi>Pſalme, Doctrine, &amp;c.</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then concernes our preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: The firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> a <hi>Pſalme</hi> was not ſo <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly,</hi> as hee maketh it, <hi>ſome ſudden</hi> to wit, extraordinary <hi>motion of the ſpirit</hi> &amp;c. The ſcriptures rather inſinuate the contrary, and that theſe Pſalmes and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſonges were alſo (beſides the Pſalmes of <hi>Dauid</hi>) and thoſe then made by extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary motion (which I will not deny) euen ordinary and conceaued by ordinary men and motions. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.18.19. <hi>Col.</hi>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:173852:20"/>3.16. <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.13. The ſcriptures are to be extended as largely, and to as common uſe, as may be, neither is any thing in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be accounted extraordinary, ſaue that which cannot poſſibly be ordinary, which theſe might bee. <hi>For the findeng out of ſweet mater</hi> they had <hi>admirable</hi> divine books to read, even the wonderfull divine ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; For muſicke, as without doubt many in that moſt rich and delicate City, were expert in it, ſo what reaſon he hath to require for the Church ſinging then in uſe, ſuch ſtudy, and art, I ſee not, except it be becauſe he dwels too neere a cathedral Church. Hee may ſee for the plaineneſſe of ſinging uſed in former times (and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſpouſe of Chriſt the Church, in all her ordinances was by Antichriſt ſtripped of her homely but comely attire, and tricked up with his whoriſh orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) that which <hi>Auſtin</hi> hath of this matter, <hi>Confeſſ. l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</p>
                  <p>For the ſecond which is <hi>doctrine,</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> he but <hi>thinks there were no Doctors in Corinth.</hi> But he may well change his thoughts, if he both conſider how that Church aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (in the body of it) even to exceſſe, <hi>in all knowledge &amp; utterance,</hi> the Doctors two ſpeciall faculties, as alſo how this Apoſtle in this Epiſtle: <hi>c,</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 28. affirmeth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly that God had <hi>ſet in the Church,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other officers, <hi>Doctors,</hi> or <hi>Teachers.</hi> Beſides that it is enough for my purpoſe if there were any in Corinth, though not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:173852:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>officer able by ordinary gift to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver doctrine; which (conſidering the fore-ſignified ſtate of that Church, both in reſpect of <hi>Pauls</hi> miniſtery amongſt them and teſtimony of them, being in that Citty, which was the chiefe of all Greece for governement, Greece alſo being the fountaine of learning, and eloquence) can not, I think, be reaſonably denyed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To yeeld you without further diſpute that Revelation, &amp; Interpretation were</hi> (viz. only) <hi>the immediate work of the ſpirit,</hi> were in us more courteſy then wiſdom. For <hi>Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> I ſee not, but that either he himſelfe who ſpake the tongue by an extraordinary gift, or any other man that underſtood it, having ordinary ability to interpret the matter deliuered) both lawfully might, &amp; in conſcience ought ſo to doe, except he would quench the ſpirit both in reſpect of the extraordinary gift of the tongue, &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gift of interpretation: but that the Paſtor or Teacher might not doe this by his ordinary gift (which is yet a fort ſtrong enough to keep us from yeelding) were ſtrange to imagine. Beſides, let it be noted how the Apoſtle v. 13. exhorts to <hi>pray</hi> for, the gift of <hi>Interpretation:</hi> Now how a man might pray for an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and miraculous gift, which hee wholy wanted, without an extraordinary moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or promiſe, and meerely upon the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles exhortation generall, I ſee not, but would learn of him that could teach me.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="8" type="argument">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:173852:21"/>
                  <head>M. Yates. ARG. 8.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FROM preſent Revelation v.</hi> 30. <hi>In the verſe going before is laid down in what order they ſhall propheſie, even as it was before for ſtrange tongues: yet here is a further injunction and that is of ſilence, if any thing of more weight ſhal be revealed unto another: why ſhould the other keep ſilence if it were known before, that this man ſhould ſpeake after him? if it were ordinary propheſying, and ſuch as our pains, and ſtudy brought us unto, then were it fit that we ſhould haue our liberty to goe on and not be interrupted by an other: but the Apoſtle up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Revelation to another even ſitting by enioyns ſilence to the preſent ſpeaker, which if his Revelation had been ſtudied before could not bee any motiue, or perſwaſion why hee ſhould yeeld to the other, that is now upon the ſudden to take his place: this were for one Prophet to diſgrace another: but the cleare ſence is to any man that will not wrangle, that becauſe it pleaſeth the ſpirit to inſpire one ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by with ſome more excellent matter, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in regard of the ſame ſubiect or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Apoſtle enioyns ſilence.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>I. Rob.</hi> ANSVV.</head>
                  <p>TO his queſtion <hi>why the former ſpeaker ſhould keep ſilence if it were knowne before that a</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. <hi>ſhould ſpeak after him</hi>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:173852:21"/>it is eaſily anſwered: that euen therefore he was to keep ſilence; that is, to take vp himſelfe in due time, as being to think in modeſty, that the conduits of the ſpirit of God did not run into his veſſell alone, but that others alſo might receaue of the fulnes of the ſame ſpirit to ſpeake ſomething further to the edification of the Church; eſpecially ſitting down in ſom appoynted place which it ſhould ſeeme verſ 30. and Act. 13.14. he that purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to propheſie vſed to take: and which order I thinke the Iewes yet obſerue in their Synagogues. And where he ads, that <hi>if it were ordinary propheſie and ſuch as our ſtudy brought vs vnto, then were it fit we ſhould haue our liberty to go on and not to be interrupted by another,</hi> which he alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts a <hi>diſgracing</hi> of the former; I would know of him whether it vvere not as fit, and much more, that the extraordinary Prophets immediatly inſpired by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, and who could not erre, ſhould haue their liberty to go on uninterrupted? Is not this vvithout all compaſſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the extraordinary Prophet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly inſpired, ſhould not haue as much liberty to goe on without being interrupted, as the ordinary, vvho might vvorthily deſerue to be interrupted for ſpeaking untruly or impertinently? al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I do not thinke that the Apoſtle requires any interrupting of the former by the later (vvhich were rude) if not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:173852:22"/>vvorſe) but onely a convenient ceſſion, or place-giving to a ſecond by the firſt ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, as hath been ſaid. Now the Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>diſgrace</hi> to the former, by the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſpeaking, is well to be minded, that it may appeare how evill cuſtomes do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the mindes of godly men, ſo as they think it a <hi>diſgrace</hi> that one ſhould giue place to another to ſpeake after him fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or otherwiſe then he hath done. But it vvas not ſo from the beginning: but ſince they, vvho under Chriſt ſhould bee ſervants of the Church, haue been her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and haue exerciſed this magiſteriall teaching now in uſe, vvhere ordinarily one alone in a Church (divers others in divers places better able then he, ſitting at his feet continually to learne) muſt be heard all his life long; thinking it a <hi>diſgrace</hi> to haue another ſpeake any thing further then he hath done: vvhich vvas the very diſeaſe in the Church of <hi>Corinth:</hi> wherein he that ſpake firſt vvould take up all the time himſelfe; vvhereas he ſhould in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty haue conceived, that a ſecond or third (eſpecially ſeeming provided to ſpeake, by ſeating themſelues in the ſame place vvith him) might haue ſomething <hi>revealed</hi> further, or othervviſe then hee had.</p>
                  <p>VVhich <hi>Revelation</hi> the Apoſtle doth not oppoſe to fore-going <hi>ſtudy</hi> (as M. <hi>Yates</hi> thinketh) but unto emulation and ſtudy of contradiction: teaching that the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:173852:22"/>ſpirit alone muſt be heard in the Church, ſpeaking by whoſe mouth ſoever. And, that there is in the Church an ordinary ſpirit of revelation; beſides comfortable experience, theſe places amongſt many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, do clearly proue, <hi>Math.</hi> 11.28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.17. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="9" type="argument">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Yates. ARG. 9.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FRom vocation,</hi> v. 29, 32.37. <hi>theſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual men are called Prophets, and to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine a Prophet without a calling, is that which the Scripture will not endure: therefore all theſe Prophets either had immediate calling from God, or mediate from men; or elſe they tooke it up themſelues: the two first we grant lawfull callings, but this intollerable. Numb.</hi> 11.28. <hi>The ſervant of Moſes ſayes, Forbid</hi> Eldad <hi>and</hi> Medad <hi>to propheſie: his reaſon was, becauſe he thought they had no calling: which had been true, if they had taken it up without immediate inſpiration: But</hi> Moſes <hi>knowing that it was from God, wiſhed that the like gift might be upon all Gods people: ſo that thoſe were true Prophets for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant by an immediate call from God: and the text ſayes, They added no further, ſhewing that as the gift ceaſed, ſo did they.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>I. Rob.</hi> ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>IT is true, that <hi>Spirituall men are called Prophets,</hi> or rather, Prophets Spirituall men: what is it then that makes a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:173852:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>man, but a gift of the ſpirit? and what a prophet ordinary or extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but the gift of propheſie ordinary or extraordinary? vvhereupon it followeth undeniably, that ſo many vvith us, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvhere, as haue the ordinary gift or abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to propheſie, are prophets, though out of office. In this Argument he hath made a ſnare vvherewith himſelfe is taken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoydably. Secondly, vve affirme, that our prophets haue a calling, which I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared formerly, not to make them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets by condition or eſtate, for that they are by their gift, but for the uſe or exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the ſame gift before beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them by the Lord, through their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and induſtry. Of <hi>Eldads</hi> and <hi>Medads</hi> propheſying we ſhall ſpeake hereafter: onely note vve in the meane vvhile, how M. <hi>Yates,</hi> and rightly, apportioneth their propheſying to their gift, as wee doe alſo ours: according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Having then gifts differing, according to the grace that is given to us, whether propheſie, let us propheſie according to the proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faith: or a miniſtery, let us wayt on the miniſtery, Rom.</hi> 12.6.7. They then that haue a gift, muſt propheſie according to their proportion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="10" type="argument">
                  <head>
                     <hi>M. Yates.</hi> ARG. 10.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FRom diſtinction, v.</hi> 37. <hi>the Apoſtle from the whole Church turnes himſelfe to their Prophets, and ſpirituall men, ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:173852:23"/>plainly, that theſe had ſome particular place aboue the reſt: and he giues them ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all charge to obſerue the things he writes to the Church: therefore thoſe were in ſome cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling aboue others: and to imagine the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is to run wide of the current of the whole Scripture: to ſet men in publike place with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out calling, is the ſame with confuſion and diſorder.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>I. Rob.</hi> ANSVV.</head>
                  <p>THIS Argument is founded upon the groundleſſe preſumption with the former: viz. that there is in the Church no lawful calling for men able to propheſy, but by officing them. And for <hi>Pauls turning his ſpeach to the Prophets.</hi> v. 37. it ſhewes indeed, that they were <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the reſt,</hi> after a ſort: and ſo they are with us rightly preferred before others, which want that endowment of the ſpirit, by which they are enabled to ſpeake to the edification of the Church.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Confirmation of the Scriptures and reaſons brought in my book to proue publick propheſying out of office by an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gift.</head>
               <p>AND before wee come to examine M. <hi>Yates</hi> his Anſwers to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures by me produced, I deſire the Reader to obſerue with mee theſe two
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:173852:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>things. Firſt, that I do not affirme in my book, that all the there alleadged Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are meant of ordinary propheſy; but that the ſame is proved by them. Neither will he (I preſume) deny, but that many things are ſufficiently proved from a ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by neceſſary conſequence, and iuſt proportion, beſides the particular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly intended in it. 2. That M. <hi>Yates</hi> ſo puts the queſtion, as that it is hard to ſay, whether he do mee, or himſelfe the more iniury: namely, whether <hi>the places prove an ordinary gift of propheſy out of office.</hi> For, as I do not ſay, that they proue the gift, but the uſe, and exerciſe of the gift be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed by God whether ordinary, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, ſo neither would he haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied (had he not leaped, before hee had lookt) but that others beſides miniſters, haue an ordinary gift of propheſie. Where the Apoſtle requires of him <hi>that deſires the office of a Biſhop,</hi> that he be <hi>apt to teach,</hi> 1. Tim. 3.1.2. <hi>and able to exhort with ſound doctrine</hi> Tit. 1.9. doth he not therein moſt evidently teach, that the gift and ability to teach, preach, and propheſy, not onely may, but muſt, both be and appeare to be in the perſon to be called to the office of miniſtery? He that is not a prophet, or hath not the gift of propheſying or preaching, (for by his gift he is a Prophet, &amp; by the uſe of it he occupies the place of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) before he be appointed a Paſtor, is an Idol ſheepheard ſet up in the temple of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:173852:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>God: neither doth the office either giue, of ſo much indeed as encreaſe the gift, but onely giues ſolemne commiſſion, &amp; charge to uſe it.</p>
               <p>The firſt Scripture by mee brought, is <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.29. where <hi>Moſes</hi> the man of God <hi>wiſheth that the whole people of the Lord were Prophets, the Lord putting his ſpirit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This place,</hi> ſaith <hi>M. Yates</hi> in his Anſ. <hi>ſpeaks of the powring out of the Spirit in an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary manner, as may apear by the occaſion of the ſpeech v.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where alſo in a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious manner (as his manner is) hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the gift of propheſying given to the 70. Elders to haue been extraordinary: which as I deny not, ſo neither needed he to haue proved. But this I affirm, that hence is proved the lawfulneſſe of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary propheſying out of office by men en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled thereunto. And firſt, as <hi>Moyſes wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth that all the Lords people were Prophets, the Lord giving his ſpirit unto them;</hi> ſo the miniſter may and ought to wiſh that the Lord would ſo bleſſe the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry endeavours of his people now, by his ſpirit, as that they all might bee Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, that is, able for gifts to ſpeak to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification. The miniſter which deſireth not this, envieth for his own, and the Clergies ſake, which <hi>Moſes would not that Ioſhua</hi> ſhould do for his. Secondly <hi>Moſes</hi> makes it all one to be a Prophet, and to haue the Lord putting his Spirit upon a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:173852:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>man. Now if the Lords ſo giving his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit unto a man, as that he be thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled extraordinarily to propheſy, make him an exrraordinary prophet, why ſhould not by due proportion, ſuch a gift of the Spirit given by the Lord to a man, as by which hee is enabled to propheſy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily, ſerue alſo to make him an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Prophet? and ſo by conſequence, if there be amongſt us any though out of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice ſo enabled to propheſy, or preach, what hindreth them from being Prophets even of the Lords own making by his ſpirits gift, and work upon their ſtudy, &amp; endevours? And if they be Prophets then may they Propheſie; which <hi>Moſes</hi> alſo in that place inſinuates: for in wiſhing that they were all Prophets, he wiſheth as wel the uſe, as the poſſeſſion of the gift. <hi>M. Yates</hi> may ſee a very leraned man <hi>Io. Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phius</hi> in his Com. upon 2. King. 23. ſhewing by this place the liberty of private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians that are able to ſpeak, and teach not onely in ordinary congregations, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in moſt ſolemne Councels.</p>
               <p>The next place is 2. Chron. 17.7. where King <hi>Iehoſophat ſent his Princes to teach in the Cities of Iudah, and with them the Levites &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M <hi>Yates</hi> accounts it <hi>a monſtrous conceit</hi> that <hi>the princes ſhould be publique teachers, which</hi> ſaith he <hi>were onely by theyr preſence and authority to back the Levites:</hi> adding that <hi>the tranſlation is mended by Iunius and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:173852:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>Tremelius &amp;c.</hi> but if the Iewes heard him (profeſſing the knowledge of <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; the <hi>Prophets</hi>) ſo ſpeak, they would marvayle at his ignorance of a thing ſo frequent and euident in theyr writings: with whom it is and ever hath been a receiued truth, that any of theyr (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>wiſe men;</hi> as <hi>they</hi> after the ſcriptures, <hi>math.</hi> 23.34. 1 cor. 1.20. Ier. 18.18. call them, may and ought to teach in theyr ſynagogues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect had to office: neither doth the tranſlation of <hi>Iunius and Tremelius</hi> by any neceſſity make for him: neyther can it be ſet agaynſt me without violence to the originall: from the ſimplicity where of they do (with due reuerence vnto them be it ſpoken) ſeeme vnto me ſomething to turne aſide in the 8 vers. <hi>Pagnine,</hi> the 70 <hi>Interpreters, Ierom,</hi> and all our <hi>Engliſh Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> carry it directly to our ſenſe. And if the <hi>conceite</hi> be <hi>monſtrous</hi> that theſe <hi>princes preached publickly,</hi> it is not bred onely in my brain: the very ſame Scripture ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been alledged very lately by the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Profeſſor in the Vniverſitie of <hi>Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> in a ſolemne aſſembly, as expreſly proving it lawful for others then miniſters to teach publickly. And becauſe much weight lieth upon this ground, which yet hee thinketh very ſandy and light, I will make it cleare to all indifferent mens iudgments, that theſe Princes, &amp; ſo others in Iſrael, and Iudah (though no Levites, nor Church officers) might lawfully teach
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:173852:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>and preach publickly in the Temple, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, and Cities.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, all Princes, Magiſtrates, Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and Governours were bound to open expound, and apply the Lawes by which they governed, according to the ſeverall occaſions offered; otherwiſe they ruled by tiranny, and appetite: which lawes for all the adminiſtrations even of the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth were onely the written word of God: wherupon I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, that if to open, expound, &amp; apply the word of God, be to preach, and teach, they then had not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly power, but charge ſo to doe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It may appeare what theſe Princes of <hi>Ichoſaphat</hi> (partaking of his power) were to do in this caſe, by that which he himſelfe, and other godly Kings haue done. The ſumme of his moſt pithy ſermon wee haue recorded. 2. Chron. 19. unto the Iudges. v. 6.7. and unto the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites v. 9.10.11. as alſo his divine prayer unto God in the publick Congregation. <hi>c.</hi> 20.5.6. &amp;c. Likewiſe the excellent ſermon of King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> unto the Prieſts, and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, in the very temple, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.4.5 &amp;c. alſo of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> with others, <hi>teaching the people the Law of the Lord.</hi> Neh. 8.10: the Kings, and Princes being as ſhepheards to feed the people, as by government, ſo by inſtruction in the Law of their God. Deſcend wee down lower to the time of Chriſt, and we ſhall ſee this matter put out of all queſtion. Doe wee not read every where how that the Scribes, Phariſees,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:173852:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Lawyers did teach publickly amongſt the Iewes; of whom yet many were no Levits or Church officers, but indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of any tribe, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.5. And if it were not the received order in Iſraell of old, for men out of office to ſpeake, and teach in publick, how was <hi>Ieſus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Mary</hi> admitted to <hi>diſpute in the Temple with the Doctors? Luk.</hi> 2.46. and to teach, <hi>and preach in the Synagogues</hi> ſo commonly as he did? <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.35. <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.16.17. &amp; how were <hi>Paul, and Barnabas, ſitting down in the Synagogue, ſent unto, after the lecture of the Law by the ruler, that if they had any word of exhortation unto the people, they ſhould ſay on?</hi> Act. 13.14.15.</p>
               <p>But if any manſhall anſwer, that theſe were extraordinary perſons, &amp; ſo taught by an extraordinary gift, he ſpeaks the truth, but to no purpoſe. For what was that to the order received in the Temple, and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, and to the Rulers thereof, who did not beleeue in Chriſt, nor acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge either his, or his Apoſtles authority; but onely admitted them unto the uſe of their gift, as they would haue done, and did ordinarily, any other men able to teach: as alſo the rulers of the Synagogues of the Iewes do at this day.</p>
               <p>The third place is miſtaken by the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in omitting only one prick, which was corrected in many Coppies, &amp; might, eaſily haue been obſerved by the Reader, For Ier. 50.45. it ſhould be Ier, 50.4.5.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:173852:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>M. Yates</hi> therefore upon that Scripture refutes his own gueſſe, and not my proofe.</p>
               <p>The fourth place is <hi>Math.</hi> 10.1.5.6. where <hi>Chriſt calling unto him his twelue Diſciples</hi> ſends them to preach <hi>the Kingdom of heauen to the loſt ſheep of Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His anſwer is, <hi>that the twelue Apoſtles were called into office, and had their calling from the firſt election of Chriſt, but had a further confirmation after, and greater mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Gods Spirit to lead them into al truth, as a Iuſtice of peace may bee put in office and yet receiue a further Confirmation, yea and greater means to performe his place.</hi> I affirme on the other ſide, (and ſhall evidently proue it God aſsiſting mee) that theſe twelue were not actually poſſeſſed of their Apoſtleſhip, till after Chriſts Reſurrection but were onely Apoſtles elect, as you call him the <hi>Major elect,</hi> who hath not the office of <hi>Major</hi> committe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to him of a good ſpace after. Neither am I herein <hi>of the minde with the Papiſts</hi> (to put <hi>M. Yates</hi> out of feare) <hi>that Peter was not in office until Chriſt gaue him charge to feed his ſheep. Ioh.</hi> 21. (which yet I am perſwaded never Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt held of his Apoſtleſhip, but of his primacy, and univerſall headſhip, or Biſhoprick) but of the ſame mind, wherof himſelf is in his firſt argument, to wit, that his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion Apoſtolick was actually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon him ioyntly with the reſt.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn,</hi> 20.22.23.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Now if the Commiſſion Apoſtolike
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:173852:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>were but then given, they were but then, and not before actually Apoſtles, except he will ſay they were Apoſtles, before they had commiſſion, that is calling fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt ſo to bee. I would now ſee how hee can ſalue the wound, which he hath giuen himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. After that the Lord Ieſus had <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.11. preferred <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> aboue all the Prophets which were before him, he yet ads in the ſame place, that <hi>the leaſt in the Kingdom of heauen is greater then hee. The leaſt.</hi> i. the leaſt Miniſter; <hi>In the kingdom of heauen.</hi> i. in the Church of the new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment properly called, which began not till after the death of Chriſt who liued and dyed a member of the Iewiſh Church. The Apoſtles then being officers of the Church of the new teſtament, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, and not of the old or Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſh Church, it cannot bee that they were Apoſtles in act, before Chriſts death; except an adiunct can be before the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, and an officer before the corporation in and of which he is an officer.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſidering the ignorance of theſe diſciples at that time in the main miſteries of Chriſt: of the nature of his kingdom, his death and reſurrection, <hi>Math,</hi> 20.21. <hi>Luke.</hi> 24.20.21. &amp;c. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 20.9. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.14. as alſo, how vtterly vnfurniſhed they were of gifts befitting Apoſtolicall teaching (for which (as being an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary diſpenſation, &amp; that in the higheſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:173852:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>degree) extraordinary, and infallible reuelation and direction of the ſpirit was requiſite, wherewith they were but firſt, (as it ſeemeth) ſprinckled <hi>Iohn.</hi> 20.22. and afterwards more plentifully filled at the day of Pentecoſt) they were as fit for an Apoſtleſhip as <hi>Dauid</hi> was for <hi>Sauls armour</hi> which he could not weild nor <hi>go with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Beſides, if they had the office of Apoſtleſhip committed to them <hi>Math.</hi> 10. how was it that they continued not their miniſtration in that office; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneing after a few dayes to their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Chriſt, continued with him as his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples till his death. Chriſt Ieſus did not keepe a company of non-reſidents about him for his Chaplins, as M. <hi>Yates</hi> inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates againſt him.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, we are expreſly taught, Eph. 4.8 11. <hi>When Chriſt aſcended on high, hee gaue gifts unto men, Apoſtles, Prophets, &amp;c.</hi> The Apoſtles then were firſt given actually at the Lords aſcenſion, and vvere before onely deſigned to become Apoſtles, or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles elect, but not ordained, nor poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of any office: and therefore preached, and that vvith warrant from Chriſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out office.</p>
               <p>The next Scripture is, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.39. by M. <hi>Yates</hi> thus opened: <hi>Chriſt having delivered the man poſſeſſed, bids him go, and ſhew what great things God had done for him: and it is ſayd he went and preached (that is, if it be to their purpoſe) by ordinary pains and ſtudy, he
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:173852:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>preached the Goſpel.</hi> And with pitty upon us <hi>poore ſoules that cannot diſtinguiſh the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of a miracle, and the gift</hi> (hee ſhould ſay the worke, if hee diſtinguiſhed as he ought) of preaching; he addeth, that <hi>if Chriſt had minded to haue made him a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like preacher, hee would firſt haue taken him with him, and inſtructed him, and then haue ſent him abroad.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, let it be obſerued, that the word uſed by <hi>Mark</hi> for his preaching,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> is the ſame word which is commonly uſed for the moſt ſolemne preaching, that is, by the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts. Secondly, Chriſt bids him, <hi>Mark.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Goe home and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare how great things the Lord had done for him, and had had compaſſion on him, and v.</hi> 20. <hi>he</hi> is ſaid to haue <hi>publiſhed in Decapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis (Luke</hi> hath it, <hi>throughout the whole Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) how great things Ieſus had done for him.</hi> VVhich he doing, what elſe did hee, but preach, publiſh, and declare the great loue and mercy of God, in and by Ieſus Chriſt towards miſerable ſinners for the curing of their bodily and ſpiritual mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies? Thirdly, where he makes the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of this miracle</hi> and <hi>the preaching of the Goſpell divers things,</hi> and pitties us <hi>poore ſoules that we cannot diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them:</hi> as Chriſt bad the <hi>women of Ieruſalem, not to weep for him, but for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues;</hi> ſo ſurely had he need to pitty not us herein, but himſelfe in his ſo great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking. Are not the miracles of Chriſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:173852:29"/>ſtoried in the Scriptures a maine part of the Goſpell? and the publiſhing of them a part of the preaching of the Goſpell? And when M. <hi>Yates</hi> opens and publiſhes a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of Chriſts (as this man did) doth he not as well and as truely preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell as at any other time? Let the wiſe iudge, who is to be <hi>pittied.</hi> To ſhut up this poynt, it is ſayd <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.30. that <hi>Ieſus did many other ſignes,</hi> &amp;c. and v. 31. <hi>But theſe are written that yee might beleeue that Ieſus is the Chriſt, the Sonne of God, and that beleeving, yee might haue life through his name.</hi> The publiſhing then of the ſignes and miracles which Chriſt did, is the preaching of faith in his name, to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: which this man therefore did, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially amongſt them which were not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and promiſe of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to come: which, by his glorious miracles done by his own pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and in his owne name, he both declared and proved himſelfe to be. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.36. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.37.38. And where he ads, that <hi>Chriſt gaue this man commiſſion to doe that which he did, but he admires who gaue ours any ſuch authority,</hi> I anſwer, even the ſame Chriſt, as then immediatly, ſo now me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly by thoſe unto whom he hath given authority under himſelfe, for the ordering of the gifts of his ſpirit in his Church. And ſufficient it is for the queſtion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and me, if it appeare (as in this perſon) that Chriſt hath given commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:173852:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>to men out of office by an ordinary gift, to publiſh, and preach in publick the the Goſpel of ſalvation.</p>
               <p>I doe quote next in my booke, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.1.—9. which for that <hi>W.E.</hi> omitteth, and leaues out, <hi>M. Yates</hi> thanketh God; but in truth hee hath more cauſe to thanke him, for ſparing him in a place which ſo pregnantly proveth the preaching of the <hi>kingdom of God</hi> by men out of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: except hee can aſſigne ſome new found office, and the ſame but of two or three dayes laſting, as v. 17. to thoſe 70 there ſent.</p>
               <p>VVe are in the next place to come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.28.29.39. which hee openeth and anſwereth with admiration, as the former place, withpitty and compaſsion, on this manner, <hi>O ſimplicity, with contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to his own writing. Simplicity that cannot ſee bttween preaching of the Goſpell, and carrying tydings of a man that told her</hi> (to wit, the woman of <hi>Samaria) of al things that ever ſhe did, is not this</hi> (ſayth ſhe) <hi>the Chriſt? But beſides ſimplicity, here is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction: for ſayes M.</hi> Robinſon, <hi>and that truely, a woman is not ſuffered to exerciſe an ordinary gift of propheſie in the Church; and ſhall the woman of Samaria ſerue your turne that it is lawfull for men to exerciſe ſuch a gift?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is indeed my <hi>ſimplicitte</hi> to think that the Goſpell (as the word importeth) is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but glad tydings: and that to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:173852:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>preach the Goſpell is nothing elſe but to carry or bring glad tydings of Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore promiſed, then come into the world. It is alſo my <hi>ſimplicity</hi> to think, ſince by the tydings which this woman brought, <hi>many of the Samaritans beleeved on Chriſt</hi> in a meaſure, v. 39. and that <hi>without preaching of the word of God, none can beleeue, Rom.</hi> 10 14.17, that therfore ſhe preached unto the Samaritans the ſame word of God in a meaſure alſo, and that as truly and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as ever M. <hi>Yates</hi> did to his pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, though ſhe went not up into a pulpit as he doth. And that he may iudge aright of this matter, let him call to minde, that thoſe Samaritans received the bookes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as did the Iewes: and as they, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> or Chriſt promiſed to, and of <hi>Abraham:</hi> bearing themſelues for the children of the Patriarks, and true worſhippers of God, as they had been, v. 20.28. and being ſo prepared, were eaſily made as <hi>regions,</hi> or <hi>corne fields white unto the Harvest, v.</hi> 35. And ſo this woman, by declaring unto them that, by which this Ieſus, the ſonne of <hi>Mary,</hi> proved himſelfe to be the Chriſt, or <hi>Meſſias</hi> promiſed, preached faith unto them moſt properly and effectually, even that main poynt of faith then in controverſie both in Iudaea and Samaria, and Galilee, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries thereunto adioyning; which was, that <hi>Ieſus was the Chriſt.</hi> I ſuppoſe M. <hi>Yates</hi> hath not ſufficiently thought of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:173852:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>theſe things, and do hope, that in godly modeſty he will ſuffer himſelfe to be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter informed.</p>
               <p>And for <hi>contradiction,</hi> between theſe two propoſitions: <hi>A woman may not teach in the Church,</hi> and <hi>A woman may teach out of the Church,</hi> or where no Church is (as it was in Samaria) it muſt be by other Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke, then I haue learnt: But hee will then demand as he doth, how this <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans preaching can ſerue my turn?</hi> I anſwer, very well, by good conſequence of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, thus: If a woman may lawfully teach out of the Church to the begetting of faith, as this woman did, but not in the Church, becauſe ſhe is a woman by ſex: then a man, againſt whom that reaſon of reſtraint of Sex lieth not, may lawfully teach both without and within the Church. Of which conſequence more hereafter.</p>
               <p>Another Scripture is, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.1.4. with chap. 11.19.20.21. where it is recorded, how <hi>all the Church at Ieruſalem was ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red abroad, except the Apoſtles, and that they which were ſcattered abroad, went every where preaching the word, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M. <hi>Yates</hi> anſwereth, <hi>that beſides the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles which were in office, there were ſeventy diſciples, which Chriſt before his death had made labourers in his harvest: and therefore theſe might preach, or any other that had an extraordinary giſt of propheſie: the one by vertue of his office and gift together, the other
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:173852:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>by commiſſion from the Holy Ghoſt to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe that gift which they had received in the day of Pentecoſt, or any other. But ſayes your Authour, compare this place with Acts</hi> 11.19.20.21. <hi>and the truth will fully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. I anſwer, it will fully appeare againſt you: for Chriſt charged both his Apoſtles, and likewiſe the</hi> 70. <hi>Diſciples, that they ſhould preach to none but the Iewes: and therefore it is ſufficient that they had ſo many preachers in office already by the commiſſion of Chriſt, to goe through all thoſe places: neither will</hi> I <hi>deny, that there might bee others whom the Holy Ghoſt immediatly raiſed up to manifeſt the excellent gifts that were to be powred down upon the Church in the primitiue times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His anſwer is very dark &amp; ambiguous, but in which are contained ſundry errors evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent enough. Firſt, he makes thoſe of the diſperſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> 
                  <hi>went about preaching the word, to be of the</hi> 70 <hi>diſciples.</hi> Luk. 10. and <hi>others the like</hi> furniſhed with an <hi>extraordinary gift of propheſie:</hi> but ſeems to allow them for no officers, in the beginning of his anſwer, when he thus ſpeaketh, <hi>Beſides the Apoſtles which were in office, there were</hi> 70. <hi>Diſciples</hi> &amp;c. yet afterwards in theſe words, <hi>and therefore it is ſufficient, that they had ſo many preachers in office already by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Chriſt to goe thorough all theſe places, &amp;c,</hi> he beſtowes ſome office or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, upon them. Secondly, hee miſſeth in two Scriptures which in his anſwere, hee pointeth at: the former is <hi>Act.</hi> 2.4
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:173852:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>where he gathereth, that others beſides, the twelue, received the gift of propheſie extraordinary at the day of Pentecoſt: the ſecond (if I miſtake not) is <hi>Math.</hi> 10.5.6. where he racks the edict or prohibition of Chriſt layed upon the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and (as he ſaith) <hi>upon the</hi> 70. <hi>Diſciples, of preaching to any but Iewes,</hi> far aboue the reach therof; even unto this time of the diſperſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it reached onely to the death of Chriſt, when the wall of partition between Iewes and Gentiles was broken downe: after which they were by the expreſſe words of their Commiſſion to preach to all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>beginning</hi> indeed <hi>at Ieruſalem and tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying there, till they were indued with power from on high,</hi> and ſo proceeding <hi>unto all nations.</hi> Luk. 24.47.49. as it is alſo recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Act.</hi> 11.20. that <hi>ſome</hi> of this diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>preached the L. Ieſus to the Grecians in Antioch.</hi> Thirdly, it is plain by that which I haue formerly ſaid, that neither theſe 70 diſciples (no nor the 12.) were by Chriſt poſſeſſed of any office before his death; no nor yet furniſhed with any extraordinary gifts of propheſie: the Evangeliſt (who knew well, and is worthy to be beleeved) bearing alſo witneſſe with mee, <hi>that the Holy Ghoſt was not yet given, becauſe that Ieſus was not yet glorified, Iohn.</hi> 7.39.</p>
               <p>Laſtly it is altogether unreaſonable to imagine that they who were ſcattered, &amp; preached abroad, being the body of the Church at Ieruſalem (excepting the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles)
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:173852:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>were all officers: and little more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to think that they were all extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily indued with the ſpirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie. For firſt, there is no circumſtance in the text leading that way: and to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine extraordinary, and miraculous things without good evidence, is extraordinary licentiouſneſſe, and preſumption. 2. the onely titles giuen unto them are; <hi>all the Church which was at Ieruſalem, they that were ſcattered abroad:</hi> and againe <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>they which were ſcattered abroad, ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Cyprus, &amp; Cyrene,</hi> &amp;c. nothing inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating any office of miniſtry. 3. Their prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching here &amp; there is onely noted to be by reaſon of their ſcattering hither &amp; thither through perſecution, and not of any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary gift, and diſpenſation commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto them. Fourthly, if they had been extraordinary Prophets immediately, and extraordinarily inſpired, there had been no need of ſo ſpeedy ſending of <hi>Barnabas</hi> from Ieruſalem to Antioch with ſupply, though hee were <hi>a man full of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> for ſo were ſuch Prophets as well as he <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20. &amp; 3.5. I conclude there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as before that theſe mens preaching was by a gift, and liberty, common unto them and us.</p>
               <p>The next Scripture is 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10, 11. <hi>As every man hath receiud the gift ſo miniſter the ſame one to another as good ſtewards of the manifold grace of God; If any man ſpeak, let him ſpeak as the oracles of God. If any
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:173852:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>man miniſter let him do it, as of the abilitie which God giveth, that God in all things may bee glorified, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This</hi> (ſaith M. Yates) <hi>is little to he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, onely thus much: would the Apoſtle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, that wee ought to be harberous one of another, and that without grudging, becauſe all that we haue is given us of God, who hath left us not as ingroſſers of his benefits, but as good diſpoſers to his glory and our brothers good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that but veiweth the place without preiudice, cannot but ſee, that <hi>the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle would perſwade</hi> more then ſo <hi>much:</hi> and that M. <hi>Yates</hi> doth iniuriouſly encloſe the Apoſtles words, v. 10. to verſe 9. which though they ly in common to both, yet belong much more to the verſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. Verſe 9. Hee exhorteth to hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitality, and verſe 10. riſeth from that particular to the more generall uſe of all gifts, or graces, and ſo verſe. 11. brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, for example, two ſpecialties: 1. the gift of propheſie in ſpeaking: 2. the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtering of the ability which God giveth bodily or otherwiſe in the Church. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can the Apoſtles meaning without extreame violence bee reſtrained to v. 9. which ſpeaks onely of hoſpitality: which is but the uſe or miniſtering of that one gift or grace of liberality. Hee ſaith in the tenth verſ. <hi>As every man hath received the gift;</hi> that is as one hath received this gift, another that, and every one ſome:
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:173852:33"/>
                  <hi>ſo miniſter the ſame one to another:</hi> that is, ſo let every ſuch perſon mutually in the bond of loue, as verſe 8. communicate his gift: <hi>as good diſpoſers of the manifold grace of God:</hi> that is, knowing that every one what gift ſoever he hath received, is but as the Lords Steward therein. Is <hi>Liberality</hi> alone <hi>a manifold grace?</hi> and <hi>Hoſpitality</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone <hi>the miniſtring of a manifold grace of God?</hi> To the miniſtring of <hi>a manifold grace,</hi> the Apoſtle perſwades, and therefore not <hi>onely that we ought to be harborous one to another,</hi> which is but the miniſtring of one grace.</p>
               <p>Two other Scriptures from the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> follow. The former is chap. 11. v. 3. <hi>I will giue to my two witneſſes, and they ſhall propheſie a thouſand two hundred ſixty dayes, cloathed in ſackcloath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is meant</hi> (ſayth M. <hi>Yates) of the two Teſtaments, and the inſtruments that God ſhould raiſe up to uſe as faithfull witneſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Antichriſt: but what is this for an ordinary gift of propheſie? Surely in this there is ſome extraordinary thing, becauſe it is ſayd God will giue power, that is, giue them life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: for Antichriſt did kill theſe witneſſes when he ſtopped the current of the holy word of God, and ſhut the mouthes of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His expoſition I will not deny (nor need to feare) ſaue as with great partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on the clergies part, he makes <hi>the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the word of God,</hi> that is, men in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:173852:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>office, the onely <hi>faithfull witneſſes againſt Antichrist.</hi> VVhereas the contrary is moſt true; and that in Antichriſts reigne no Church-officer, as an officer, witneſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, but all for him: as both ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their authority by him, and binding themſelues to ſubmit their doctrine to his cenſure. The perſons indeed, that were alſo officers, even Maſſe-prieſts, Monkes and Friers, witneſſed ſome of them againſt him, but ſo did not their offices, or they in reſpect of them, (which is all one) but rather with him, as advantaging his ſtate and Hierarchy. Something extraordinary I do vvith him acknowledge to haue been in them, in reſpect of the order then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing, and of the bondage ſpirituall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which all both things and perſons were: as alſo of the degree of their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary both gifts and graces to put them forth in ſervice of the truth: but that theſe witneſſes againſt Antichriſt had any extraordinary, or miraculous gift of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie (which he inſinuateth, and muſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he will draw them from our part) is meerely imagined both againſt experience and their owne plea. But for the opening of this place, I referre the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to our learned Countrey-man M. <hi>Brightman,</hi> where he ſhall finde affirmed, and proved, that theſe two prophets were <hi>the holy Scriptures, and Aſſemblies of the faithfull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other ſcripture is <hi>Reu.</hi> 14.6.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:173852:34"/>where <hi>the Angell flieth in the midſt of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven having the euerlaſting goſpell to preach vnto them that dwell on the earth, and to every nation, and kindred, and tongue, and people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By heauen</hi> (ſaith <hi>M. Yates) is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the viſible Church, and by the Angell the learned men that God hath euer raiſed vp in the midſt of popery to carry the bleſſed word of God in the midſt of heauen, that is, raiſed from the earthly corruption of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, but not as yet at the height of purity, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As I doe not conceiue of any ſuch miſtery in theſe words, <hi>(flying in the midſt of heauen)</hi> but onely that theſe Angels ſhould roundly and clearly (ſpecially in reſpect of former times) publiſh the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell far, and neere, as is the flying of a bird in the airy heauen, or firmament, ſpeedy and euident; ſo (that ſignified) I aſſent to his expoſition, as being alſo no way preiudiciall, but much aduantageable to my purpoſe. For if thoſe learned, and Angel-like men were to publiſh the goſpel in the midſt of popery; and that neither by any extraordinary, or miraculous gift, nor by vertue of their office, then is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick propheſying out of office by an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary gift approuable. The firſt part I hope he will eaſily grant; if not, let him name the man miraculouſly inſpired in the midſt of popery. For the latter, the office it ſelf or function was no miniſtery of Chriſts appoyntment, as being the office
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:173852:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>of a Frier, Monk, or Maſſe-prieſt, ſo their power to adminiſter it was from or by the pope, as vniverſall Biſhop: that is, as Antichriſt. In reſpect then of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell which they preached, and of their gifts and graces perſonall, by which they were both enabled and prouoked thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, they were Angels of God; but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their office, and power Eccleſiaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, and Hierarchicall, Angels of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. Beſides that when they gaue their cleareſt teſtimony againſt Antichriſt, they were, for the moſt part, all excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated out of the Church of Rome: and ſo being no members, could not be officers of any Church. Whereupon I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the witneſſe which they gaue to the truth, was but perſonall, and not miniſteriall, ſo far forth as it was of God, or by him approued. And thus it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth how in the quoting of thoſe ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, we haue not <hi>offered abuſe to Gods word</hi> (as he abuſeth vs) but haue with good conſcience, as in the ſight of God, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them as ſeruing to proue lawfull, publique propheſie by an ordinary gift out of office.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. comes into handle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with the proofes thence taken: which what weight they haue, ſhall appeare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rehearſall of ſome more generall conſiderations premiſed in my book, in the ſame place, for the better vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the poynt. as. 1. <hi>that the Church of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:173852:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>Corinth aboue all other Churches, did abound with ſpirituall gifts both ordinary, and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary.</hi> 2. <hi>that they abuſed theſe giftes too much vnto faction and ambition.</hi> 3. <hi>that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon the Apoſtle takes occaſion in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the</hi> 12. <hi>Chap. and ſo forward, to draw them to the right vſe of theſe gifts of God, which was the imployment of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the edifiing of the body in loue.</hi> 4. and laſtly, <hi>that hauing layd down ch.</hi> 13. <hi>a full deſcription &amp; large co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation of that grace of loue, ch.</hi> 14 <hi>&amp; the beginning of it,</hi> he <hi>exhorts to propheſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to the ſtudy and vſe of that gift; which though it were not ſo ſtrange a thing as was the ſudden gift of tongues, nor which drew with it ſuch wonder and admiration, yet was it more profitable for the Church: and though a matter of leſſe note, yet of greater charity, which muſt beare ſway in all our actions.</hi> VVhereupon I lay downe the firſt reaſon for brethrens (though no officers) liberty in theſe words: <hi>Becauſe the Apoſtle ſpeakes of the manifeſtation of a gift, or grace com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all perſons, as well brethren as mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, ordinary as extraordinary, and that at all times, which is loue: as alſo of ſuch fruits and effects of that grace, as are no leſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all, then the grace it ſelfe, nor of leſſe continuuance in the Churches of Chriſt, to wit, of edification, exhortion, and comfort, v.</hi> 3. <hi>compared with</hi> 1. Theſſ. 5.11.14.</p>
               <p>In anſwering the former part of the Reaſon hee is very large but more negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, as appears in his <hi>denying, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:173852:35"/>ſpeaks of a gift common to all perſons</hi>) and in more then denying, (for his rude terme I will conceale for his credits ſake) that it was <hi>common to all perſons at all times admiring how I dare affirme any ſuch thing:</hi> adding: <hi>that loue was enioyned to all but this gift onely of ſuch, as did excell amongſt them:</hi> whereas the very gift, which I ſpeak of in that place, or <hi>grace</hi> rather, as I there call it, was none other, but the grace of loue; as any that will may ſee in the reaſon: which generall grace ought to manifeſt, and expreſſe it ſelfe in the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uſe of all the ſpecial gifts of the ſpirit: which by it are ſet a work &amp; moued, as the leſſer wheels of a clock by the greater: &amp; from which grace the Apoſtle provoketh the Church to the ſtirring up of the gift of propheſy, unto edification, as well now as then. And whereas, to my ground, (as he puts it, &amp; as after a ſort I intended, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> v. 3. compared with 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.11.14. viz. that ſince the end which is edification exhortation, &amp; comfort continueth, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the gift of propheſy alſo continueth) he anſwereth; that <hi>there are many means to effect one end, &amp; yet ſome of them may ceaſe yea all of them, &amp; other come in their roomes,</hi> as, <hi>for extraordinary gifts, ordinary;</hi> and ſo for <hi>Apoſtles, ordinary miniſters:</hi> inſtancing further in <hi>tongues, which v.</hi> 26. <hi>are for edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication;</hi> he neither ſpeaks ſo properly, as is meet, nor (all admitted which he ſaith) takes away the force of the Argument.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:173852:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>Strange tongues, (to ſpeak properly, and preſſely, as in diſputing) are no means of edifying the Church; but the interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and application of the matter of the tongues: neither doth the office of the miniſtery in it ſelfe edifie, but the uſe and exerciſe of it in teaching, and exhorting; no nor yet the gift of propheſying, but as it is uſed in ſpeaking, as v. 3. <hi>hee that propheſieth,</hi> that is uſeth the gift of propheſie, <hi>ſpeaketh unto men, to exhortation edification, and comfort.</hi> There being then no other means to edify, exhort, and comfort in the Church but propheſying, the Apoſtle (as appeareth by the two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſet together) laying theſe dueties from the common grace of loue as well upon brethren, as officers, ordinary as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, &amp; at all times, in the Church, therein giues warrant to an ordinary exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of propheſie in the Church by me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of office (to wit having gifts &amp; abilities anſwerable) to the end of the world.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Argument is from v. 21. where the Apoſtle ſaith, ye <hi>may all prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie one by one, that all may learne, &amp; all may be comforted, he ſpeaks of alls propheſying as largely as of alls learning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>is abſurd: are all the Church Prophets? if all may propheſie who ſhall learn? the H. Gh. ſayes</hi> all, <hi>but that is to be underſtood of ſuch as haue gifts; all ought to haue the gift of hearing, but the like is not of propheſying: &amp; I ſay this gift was extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:173852:36"/>for how could all men ſtudy the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures when they had them not in their natiue tongues?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It were abſurd indeed, if I thought, that every perſon in the Church were to propheſie: but why ſhould hee chalendge mee, or I purge my ſelfe of this abſurdity? whereas the contrary is moſt evident, both in the words of the queſtion, which are, <hi>that others having receiued a gif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thereunto, may and ought to ſtir up the ſame, and to uſe it in the Church;</hi> and every where in the handling of it. By <hi>all</hi> then I meane all that haue gifts: and ſo take <hi>all</hi> for propheſying as largely (yet in the ſubiect, according to the received rule of expounding the notes of univerſality,) as the other <hi>all</hi> for learning. His queſtion, <hi>if all may propheſie who ſhall learne?</hi> is eaſily anſwered. For they who propheſie at one time may learn at another: It is the diſeaſe of the exalted Clergy to skorn to learne any thing of others then themſelues, and almoſt one of another. Where he further ſaith, that <hi>all ought to haue the gift of hearing, but the like is not propheſying,</hi> it is true, and that every particular perſon in the Church is not bound to haue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gift; but if he ſpeak any thing to the purpoſe in hand, he muſt go further, and ſay that no ordinary brethren out of office ought to haue the gift of propheſie: which if it were true, then ought none to ſtriue for fitneſſe to become officers: neither were the reproofe iuſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:173852:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>which the Apoſtle layes, not onely, nor ſo much, if at all, upon the officers, as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the brethren, Heb. 5.12. that <hi>for the time they ought to be teachers.</hi> Of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy miſtaking about the Scriptures not being in the Corinths natiue tongue, which hee makes the onely ground of his Anſwer, elſe where. To conclude this Argument. The Apoſtle writing to the Church of Corinth, <hi>ye may all propheſie one by one,</hi> cannot be underſtood of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Prophets, except we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue that the body of that Church was or might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets extrarodinary, &amp; miraculouſly inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: which, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering the ſuperexcellency of that ſtate by me elſwhere laid down, is a preſumption aboue my reach, and leaſt of all agreeing with <hi>M. Yates</hi> his iudgment in his anſwer to the next Argument, which is, that extraordinary propheſie did then begin to ceaſe in the Church.</p>
               <p>The third Argument is from v. 34. where the Apoſtle <hi>restrains wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> propheſying, or other ſpeaking in the Church with autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as alſo</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11.12. <hi>and in forbidding women, giues liberty to all men gifted accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, oppoſing women to men, ſex to ſex, and not women to officers: and againe, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining women ſhewes his meaning to be of ordinary not extraordinary propheſying: for women immediately, extraordinarily, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly inſpired might ſpeake without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, Exod,</hi> 15.20. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.36. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.17.19<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; 21.9.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:173852:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>It is a pitteous thing to ſee how M. <hi>Yates</hi> intangles himſelfe about this Argument, ſtraining all the veyns of his wit, if not of a more tender part (his conſcience) to draw ſome face of anſwer upon it: That which hath any ſhew of anſwer either in that place, or any other throughout his tedious and perplexed diſcourſe, I will relate and refute: confirming the Argument cleerly, as I am perſwaded, to any indifferent iudgement.</p>
               <p>His firſt Anſwer, or Exception is, that <hi>it is moſt abſurd to imagine that the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian women, did follow their ſtudy, and took orcinary pains to make ſermons. Secondly that extraordinary propheſie did ceaſe, and that not all at once, but firſt in wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; that the Apoſtle therefore eſpecially aims at them, as though</hi> (to wit in their own iudgement <hi>the ſame meaſure were ſtill upon them, as well as in former times; when Chriſt that ſaues both man and woman, would extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily manifeſt himſelfe in both, yet firſt after a ſufficient manifeſtation of his grace and goodneſſe, he withdrew thoſe extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary gifts from that ſex then afterward from the other.</hi> His third anſwer, upon which he doth moſt inſiſt, is, that <hi>the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle forbids two generall faults in the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; the one that they would pray, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie uncovered.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.5. <hi>imitating the</hi> Pythoniſſes <hi>and</hi> Sibilles <hi>of the Gentiles in laying aſide their vaile, and ſpreading their haire againſt decency, and comelineſſe: the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:173852:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>is that in their huſbands preſence, they would be as ready to ſpeak as they: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle finding the women to abuſe this gift, prohibits the uſe of it, whether ſimply or no, he cannot iudge. Fourthly, hee admires by what Logick this will follow; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are forbidden to propheſie, therefore men haue liberty: which</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>is an ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qnence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In his firſt Anſwer or rather exception, he miſtakes both the ſtate of the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and alſo the nature of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. The queſtion is not of the ſtudy, or ability of theſe women (which yet I think was greater then hee maketh ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of) but of their forewardneſſe to teach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, which was certainely too great. And what conſequence is this? The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthian women were not ſufficiently furniſhed to teach by an ordinary gift, therefore they needed not to bee reltrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from teaching. Nay, therefore they needed much more ſuch bridle of reſtraint to be caſt upon them; eſpecially confide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their manniſh bouldneſſe, and immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, inſinuated againſt them here by the Apoſtle, in part, but much more <hi>c.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>Neither (for the ſecond point) are they that ſpeak in the exerciſe of propheſie, to make a ſermon by an houre glaſſe, as M. <hi>Yates</hi> gathers; that were to abuſe the time, and wrong the gifts of others (but briefly to ſpeak a word of exhortation, as God enableth, and that, after the miniſteriall
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:173852:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>teaching bee ended, as Act. 13. queſtions alſo about things delivered, &amp; with them even diſputations, as there is occaſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part or apurtenances of that exerciſe, 1. Cor. 14.35. Act. 17.2. and 18.4.</p>
               <p>For the Prophets gifts &amp; abilities then, as under the Law <hi>a bullock or lambe, that had any thing ſaperfluous, or lacking in his parts might yet bee offered for a freewill offering: but for a vow it was not to be accepted.</hi> Leu. 22.23, ſo in this exerciſe of propheſie, as in a freewill offering, according to the gift of God, that which is leſſe perfit, and exact, may far better be excepted, then if the ſame were preſented in the Paſtors vowed ſervice, and miniſtration.</p>
               <p>For his ſecond Anſwer: As it is true, that <hi>extraordinary propheſie did ceaſe by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,</hi> ſo is it not certain, but a meere pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, that it <hi>ceaſed firſt in women:</hi> but moſt untrue it is, that <hi>the Apoſtle there aims</hi> at all <hi>at the ceaſing of that gift in women.</hi> Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories worthy of credit in this kind, doe teſtifie, that the ſtreame of the ſpirit was ſo far from being neare dry at this time, as that it ran a ſtrong cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent wel-nigh a hundred years after, for all the extraordinary gifts thereof, as for the caſting out of divels, foreſeing and foretelling of things to come, healing the ſick, and raiſing of the dead, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuers ſo rayſed liued many yeares after; witneſſe amongſt others <hi>Iraeneus adv. Her. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. whom alſo for the ſame purpoſe <hi>Euſ-Hiſt.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:173852:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>Eccl. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 7. alledgeth: And ever for women. Evident it is by the Scriptures that extraordinary Propheſie in a very plenteous manner by them, and that in the preſence of men continued in the Church many years after <hi>Pauls</hi> writing of this Epiſtle. <hi>Phillip the Evangelist had foure daughters virgins which did propheſie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 21.9.</note> &amp; that in the preſence of the Apoſtle. Lo, foure extraordinary propheteſſes in one houſe, and the daughters of one man: ſo that hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto the conduit of the ſpirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie kept his courſe as well upon their <hi>daughters as ſonnes.</hi> Ioel. 2. Act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. So <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.20. we read <hi>how the woman Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabell (calling her ſelfe a propheteſſe)</hi> taught and by teaching, <hi>ſeduced</hi> the Lords <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in the Church of Thyatyra.</hi> In which place, as the errors and evils of the perſon is condemned, ſo is the formall order of the Church manifeſted to be, that vvomen (propheteſſes extraordinary) might teach. Laſtly, the prohibition of vvomen by the Apoſtle is perpetuall, and not vvith reſpect to this, or that time, as appeares by the reaſons thereof, both in this place, and in the Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and ſuch as equally belong to former times, and lattter: and no more to the latter end then to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, or middle time of the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the grace and goodneſſe of Ghriſt.</p>
               <p>VVhat can be more abſurd then to ſay that theſe reaſons, <hi>The woman muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der obedience,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34. <hi>and not uſurpe authority over the man, but be in ſilence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:173852:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>Adam was firſt formed, then Eue. And Adam was not ſeduced, but the woman, &amp;c.</hi> 1. Tim. 2.12.13.14. were not morall and perpetuall? VVere not thoſe reaſons and grounds for vvomens ſilence in the Church (vvithout extraordinary diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation by miraculous inſpiration) of as great force ſeven yeares before, as vvhen <hi>Paul</hi> wrote this Epiſtle? It is therfore moſt cleare, that the Apoſtle aimes not at all, at any ceaſing of the gift of extraordinary propheſie now growing on, but at the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall, and abſolute reſtraint and prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of vvomens propheſying, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, but ordinary.</p>
               <p>In his third anſwer he dealeth vvorſe then in any of the other, in labouring to ſmother one truth under another. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the women of <hi>Corinth</hi> were become ſo manniſh, as that they would propheſie uncovered, and without their veile, (the enſigne of their ſubjection) yet doth not the Apoſtle meddle at all with that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady in this place, but in the 11. chapter of the Epiſtle, as himſelfe noteth. Here and in <hi>Tim.</hi> he ſimply forbids the thing: there the manner of doing it. Likewiſe, for their being as forward to ſpeake, as their husbands, and in their preſence, it may be true in part, and in ſome. But what then? Doth the Apoſtle in theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces onely forbid their ſpeaking uncove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and permit them to teach ſo it be vei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? or forbids he onely their being as
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:173852:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>forward as their husbands, but giues them leaue to ſpeake in the Church, ſo it bee with good maners, and after them, which his anſwer inſinuates? Or is it not evident to all that will not ſhut their eyes, that he ſimply, and that ſeverely, inhibits them all ſpeaking whatſoever in this exerciſe? Are not the words plain enough? <hi>Let the women keep ſilence in the Church, for it is not permitted to them to ſpeak, but to be under obedience, as the Law ſayth.</hi> And againe, <hi>It is a ſhame for them to ſpeake in the Church.</hi> And in 1. Tim. <hi>Let the women learne in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence with all ſubiection.</hi> And, <hi>I ſuffer not a woman to teach, nor to uſurpe authority ouer the man, but to be in ſubjection. For Adam was firſt formed, &amp;c.</hi> Do not all and every one of the Reaſons binde women to all peace and deepe ſilence in the Church, yea to ſuch and ſo abſolute, as that they may not ſo much as aske a queſtion for learning any thing themſelues, verſ. 35. much leſſe teach others any thing? I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conclude this as a moſt certain and undeniable truth, that the Apoſtle ſpeaks here of ſuch a gift and exerciſe as women are ſimply forbidden to uſe in the Church; and therefore not of an extraordinary gift or exerciſe, which they might uſe lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and did both before, and a long time after the writing of this Epiſtle.</p>
               <p>His laſt anſwer now comes in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which is, that the <hi>conſequence is ill, women are forbidden, and therefore men are
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:173852:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>permitted to propheſie in the Church by an ordinary gift.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the conſequence ſeem not good, why doth he ſo ſtrugle as before otherwiſe to make an eſcape from the Argument? let us co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider of the force of it, which appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to me irreſiſtable in theſe 3. things. Firſt, the Apoſtle in, and for this work op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth the men to the women, ſex to ſex, &amp; ſo in prohibiting women, he permits men. VVhen the H. Ghoſt oppoſing faith and workes in the caſe of iuſtification, denies that we are iuſtified by works, is not the conſequence good, that therfore we are iuſtified by faith. VVhere hee oppoſeth belevers &amp; vnbeleevers in the caſe of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and teacheth that beleevers ſhall be ſaued, doth he not teach conſequently, that vnbeleevers ſhall periſh? If theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences be not good I muſt confeſſe my ſelfe farre to ſeeke both in logick and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the reaſons of the prohibition of women prove the conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which are all ſuch as prefer the men before the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp; ſubiect the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the men in the Church, &amp; in this very work of propheſy, of which he treateth. But now if in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting women, he gaue not liberty vnto men, where were the prerogatiue of men aboue women, which is the onely ground, vpon which he buildeth his prohibition?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, where verſe 34.35. <hi>It is not permitted for women to ſpeak but if they will
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:173852:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>learn any thing to ask their huſbands at home,</hi> if their huſbands might not ſpeak neither, nor any more then they, what reaſon can be rendred of the Apoſtles ſo ſpeaking?</p>
               <p>Laſtly M. <hi>Yates</hi> in denying this conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, ſheweth, that ſo he might deny ſomething, he tooke no great heed what it were. The Apoſtle in this whole Chap. takes order for ſome to propheſy? and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barring women therefrom, either admits men to the vſe of that liberty, or els wee muſt haue ſome third kinde of perſons thought of, which are neither male nor female.</p>
               <p>My fourth Argument is from v. 29. and 32. <hi>Let the prophets ſpeak two or three, and let the reſt iudg:</hi> and <hi>the ſpirit of the prophets are ſubiect to the prophets.</hi> VVhence I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that the Apoſtle ſpeaks not of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary prophets, or propheſying, ſince they in their doctrines could not erre, and ſo were not ſubiect to any ſuch iudgment, or cenſure of others. He anſwereth round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though breifly in this place, that <hi>theſe prophets were not infallibly aſſiſted:</hi> and more largely in another place, that <hi>ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets as haue an infallible aſſiſtance are not ſubiect to this Rule: but others that had but, as the Apoſtle ſaid, Rom.</hi> 12.6. <hi>meaner gifts were to be examined according to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap> portion of faith, ſo that extraordinary prophets might mix ſome of their own with the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary gifts of Gods ſpirit, which was to be cenſured by ſuch as had a greater meaſure:
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:173852:41"/>for none are to think that all that had theſe extraordinary gifts were free from errour in their very doctrine. We ſee the ſtrange gift of tongues was abuſed, and ſo might the reſt be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That one extraordinary Prophet had a greater meaſure, and proportion of gifts then another, I acknowledge; but that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one of them could erre in doctrine, or was not infallibly aſſiſted therein by the ſpirit, I deny, as a moſt pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous errour, weakning the foundation of faith, and truth of the word of God: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath M. <hi>Yates</hi> ſo much as exterprized an Anſw. unto the Scriptures brought by me to prooue the contrary: which were Eph. 2.20. where the <hi>Epheſians as the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold,</hi> or Church <hi>of God</hi> are ſaid to bee <hi>built upon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets,</hi> &amp;c. &amp;c. 3.5. where he ſpeaks of <hi>the miſtery of Chriſt, which in other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges was not made known unto the ſonnes of men, as it is now revealed unto his holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Prophets by the ſpirit.</hi> VVhence it apeares, that the Church is as well built upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Prophets, to wit extraordinary, which then were (for of them he ſpeaketh) as upon the doctrine of the Apoſtles, and they as infalliby (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for the very foundation) inſpired by the H. Ghoſt, as the other. So that, if the Prophets could erre in doctrine, then the Apoſtles, &amp; if in doctrine taught why not written? and if one alone, why not more, or all? and if they might erre, how
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:173852:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>know we that they did not erre? If he ſay the meaner in gifts might erre, but not the greater; firſt the ſame followeth alſo tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Apoſtles, how much more touching the Prophets before Chriſt (not comparable to thoſe after him:) why then may there not be errors in the writings eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecialy of thoſe of meaner gifts, as without doubt ſome were in compariſon of the reſt? what wether this wind will bring who ſeeth not? Moreouer, whereas vvee propound ſuch interpretations and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, as we gather from the Scriptures, by diſcourſe of reaſon, and ſo may erre: they, on the contrary every one of them delivered doctrine by immediate inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſpirit, in which by reaſon of the divine impreſſion which it made in their hearts (differencing it from all both humane collection and Diabolicall ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) they could not erre, or be miſtaken, but knew infallibly when, and wherein they were moved by the H. Ghoſt. Befides there is not like reaſon of ſtrange ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, and propheſie, for the conſideration in hand, ſince the Church is not built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the foundation of ſtrange tongues, as upon the foundation of propheſie; neither was the matter of the ſpeech inſpired, but the language onely, except the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were Prophets alſo.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, if there were the like reaſon of tongues, and propheſie, yet except men might erre in a tongue, and deem them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:173852:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>inſpired extraordinarily when they were not (which were abſurd to affirme) it could not evince any poſſibility of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in doctrine, by extraordinary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</p>
               <p>The laſt Argument in my booke I take from v. 37. 38. <hi>If any man think himſelf to be a prophet, or ſpirituall, let him acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg that the things that I write unto you are the commandements of the Lord: But if any be ignorant, let him be ignorant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. Yates</hi> taxeth mee for making <hi>a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and ſpirituall man all one, ſince by a ſpirituall man is meant ſuch as excelled in any ſpirituall gift, propheſie, or other.</hi> But without cauſe, ſince I neither mean more nor need more for my purpoſe, then that a Prophet bee included in the generall of a ſpirituall man. But wherefore doth he not anſwer the Argument or minde where the force thereof lieth? which is in the words following; <hi>let him acknowledge that the things that I write are the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord. But if any man be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, let him be ignorant.</hi> The extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary prophets, were guided as immediately &amp; infallibly by the revelation of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, &amp; might as wel haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him to <hi>acknowledg that the things which they ſpeak were the commandements of the Lord,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hee of them: neither was it poſſible that they or any of them ſhould bee ignorant, that the things which hee ſpake were the commandements of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:173852:43"/>Lord. Which Argument is alſo much ſtrengthened, and made, in my iudgement, unanſwerable, by that which we finde v. 36. <hi>Came the word of God out from you, or came it unto you onely?</hi> which words the Apoſtle doth not direct unto <hi>the women</hi> (as M. <hi>Yates</hi> miſconceaveth with great errour, and contrary both unto reaſon, and to the expreſſe Greek text which will not beare it) but to the Prophets; with whom hee dealeth, and that by way of compariſon with himſelf, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom, to wit, by immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate revelation, the word of God came after a ſort to the Corinthians. VVhich plainly proues that they could not bee extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Prophets, from whom the word of God came unto the Church as well as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> himſelfe: they being inſpired immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Holy Ghoſt as well as he.</p>
               <p>The Chriſtian Reader may finde, beſides theſe, other reaſons from this Scripture laid down by our worthy countryman M. <hi>Cartwright</hi> in his <hi>Confutation of the Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, Sect.</hi> 5. for the iuſtification of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe as ordinary and continuall.</p>
               <p>The other Arguments in the ſame place of my booke to the ſame purpoſe, though M. <hi>Yates</hi> could not but take knowledge of, yet hath he not thought good to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle vvith, One of them only I will annex in this place word for word, as there I haue ſet it downe.</p>
               <p>It is the commandement of the Lord by the Apoſtle, that <hi>a Biſhop muſt be apt to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:173852:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>teach,</hi> and that ſuch <hi>Elders</hi> or <hi>Biſhops</hi> bee called as are <hi>able to exhort with ſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and to conuince the gain-ſayers,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.9. Now except men, before they bee in office may bee permitted to manifeſt their gifts in <hi>doctrine,</hi> and ſo in <hi>prayer,</hi> which are the two maine works requiring ſpeciall qualifications in the teaching Elders, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.4, how ſhall the Church (which is to chooſe them) take knowledge of their ſufficiency, that with faith and good conſcience they may call them, and ſubmit unto them for their guides? If it be ſayd, that upon ſuch occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, triall may be taken of mens gifts: he that ſo ſaith, grants the queſtion; but muſt know beſides, firſt that mens gifts and abilities ſhould be knowne in ſome meaſure, before they be once thought on for officers: and ſecondly, that there is none other uſe or triall of gifts <hi>(to wit in and by the Church)</hi> but in propheſying: for every thing in the Lords houſe is to bee performed in ſome ordinance, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thrown about the houſe, or out of order in it: and other ordinance in the Church ſaue this of propheſie is there none, wherein men out of office are to pray, and teach, &amp;c. Laſtly, <hi>M. Yates</hi> in denying this liberty, beſides other evils, reproveth the practiſe of all reformed Churches, and of the Church of <hi>England</hi> with them. It is not onely permitted as lawfull, but required as neceſſary where,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:173852:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>liue, that ſuch as haue bent their thoughts towards the miniſtery, ſhould before hand uſe their gifts publickly in the Church: and intollerable bondage it would bee thought by them to haue paſtors ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for them (as all there are unto the places in which they are to miniſter) of whoſe ability in teaching they had not taken former experience. And not onely ſo, but it hath been further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed in ſolemne Synod, <hi>that in all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches whether ſpringing up, or grown to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the order of propheſie ſhould be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, according to Pauls inſtitution; and that into that fellowſhip (to wit of Prophets) ſhould be admitted not onely the miniſters, but alſo the Teachers, and of the Elders and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, and even of the very common people</hi> (ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ipſa plebe) <hi>if there were any which would confer their gifts received of the Lord to the common benefit of the Church, &amp;c. Harmon. Synod. Belg. de prophetica. Ex Synodo Emb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dana, Can.</hi> 1.2. And for <hi>England</hi> it ſelfe; what will M. <hi>Yates</hi> ſay to the <hi>Common Places,</hi> as they are called; or Sermons, as indeed they are, in the Colledges, not onely permitted unto, but impoſed upon divers, who never receved order of Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood? VVhat to ſuch as Preach by the Biſhops licence, without any ſuch order? yea to all ſuch as are ordained and called miniſters, but haue not actuall charge, and ſo are like the Popiſh accidents in the Sacrament, without a ſubiect? Laſtly,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:173852:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>it might be ſhewed, if need were, that greater liberty then he alloweth, is uſed by divers in the Romiſh Church, the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Egipt,</hi> and houſe of bondage for Gods people: ſo as the bondage of the very <hi>Hagar</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is not ſo great in this caſe, as he would bring upon <hi>Sarah</hi> her ſelfe.</p>
               <p>The Lord giue unto his people courage to ſtand for this liberty amongſt the reſt, wherewith Chriſt hath made them free; and unto us who enioy it, grace to uſe the ſame unto his glory, in our mutuall edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. <hi>Amen,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
